<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cum bono deo. A remonstrance to the Godly party. Two maine quæries, which stand much usefull fo these our times. ... And a vindication of both. / By Andrew Logie sometime Arch-Deane of Aberdene; Penned by the author, ann. 1654, and printed 1661.</title>
            <author>Logie, Andrew.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52211868</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52211868</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175721</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175721)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2748:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cum bono deo. A remonstrance to the Godly party. Two maine quæries, which stand much usefull fo these our times. ... And a vindication of both. / By Andrew Logie sometime Arch-Deane of Aberdene; Penned by the author, ann. 1654, and printed 1661.</title>
                  <author>Logie, Andrew.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 2-39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Aberdeen] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April, 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Scotland --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Cum Bono DEO.</p>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE TO THE GODLY PARTY.</p>
            <p>Two maine <hi>Quaeries,</hi> Which ſtand much uſefull for theſe our times.</p>
            <p>The One is anent that, which made this wofull <hi>Diaphragma</hi> or <hi>Diſſepimentum,</hi> this <hi>Diviſion</hi> twixt <hi>KING, State</hi> and <hi>Church;</hi> And this is <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Other is anent that, which hath ſo pittifully rent our <hi>Church</hi> in her ſelf, &amp; ſo ſtands <hi>maceries, paries</hi> intergerinus, or intergerivus, The <hi>partition-Wall</hi> twixt our PROTESTERS, the GODLY PARTY, (as they are pleaſed out of a more then a <hi>Phariſaicall pride</hi> ſuperciliouſly to arrogate this <hi>title</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and the <hi>Aſſembly-men;</hi> So that it is turned queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable with not a few with us to day, which of theſe two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>Factions</hi> we ſhould acknowledge for our true <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Church,</hi> both theſe acclaiming <hi>in jure,</hi> this <hi>Title</hi> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>AND this is, If our <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> did rightly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine anent the receiving in, into the boſome of their Army of <hi>Nuncupative Malignants,</hi> in ſuch a nick of time &amp; exigence of <hi>Affaires,</hi> or pronounced therein <hi>clave errante. Numerò,</hi> If that <hi>Engagement</hi> ſtood lawfull with the One, or unlawfull with the Other:</p>
            <p>AND A VINDICATION of Both, By <hi>ANDREW LOGIE</hi> ſomtime <hi>Arch-Deane</hi> of <hi>Aberdene;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Penned by the <hi>Author,</hi> Ann. 1654, And printed 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OF <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Firſt <hi>Quaere</hi> ſhall be this, If <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> The OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER it ſelf may be juſtly outted, becauſe that the <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> wherby the men in the order entitled or deſigned, viz. <hi>Epiſcopus,</hi> which is rendred in our ordinary language <hi>Biſhop,</hi> doeth ſeeme to our <hi>Diſciplinarians,</hi> forſooth, <hi>ſapere faſtum,</hi> to ſavour of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>arrogancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> GOod LORD! What preſumptuous and bold, as unwarrantable ignorance is this, from off of the <hi>Name,</hi> from whence men in a CALLING receive their denomination, to raiſe <hi>grounds</hi> or <hi>reaſons</hi> to infirme and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a CALLING? Is not this <hi>Ludere in vocibus,</hi> rather then <hi>ſeriò agere,</hi> nay, <hi>impiè ludere in re tam ſeria?</hi> But to the <hi>Point.</hi> This their <hi>Alleadgeance</hi> is falſe: for this is a TITLE <hi>oneris po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs, quàm Honoris,</hi> of a burden rather, then of honour. Doth not this very NAME <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> or <hi>Overſeer,</hi> import and deſigne <hi>Curam et ſolicitudinem,</hi> which requires no little vigilancy and carefulneſſe? And ſo as <hi>Honos,</hi> or <hi>Honour</hi> is conferred to them, ſo an <hi>onus,</hi> or <hi>burden</hi> is impoſed on them, and thus it is incumbent on them, as <hi>praeſſe,</hi> ſo <hi>prodeſſe,</hi> ſince <hi>dignity</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> go together. This very <hi>Name</hi> of GODS own impoſition, is like a <hi>Memento,</hi> or as the <hi>voyce of a Cryer,</hi> to ſound out wholſome admonitions and inſtructions on both ſides: for to them, <hi>Aurem vellit et admonet,</hi> it pulleth them by the eare and admoniſheth them of the heavy burden impoſed on them, and weyghty charge entruſted them; That they ſo overſee, as men who muſt one day <hi>reddere rationem villicationis ſuae,</hi> give, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and make an accompt of their inſpection and overſight; And on the other hand, IT bears on them, who are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to their inſpection and overſight, the returne of a reciprocall duty of <hi>acknowledgement, ſubjection</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion.</hi> But I cannot
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175721:5"/>ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly wonder, That men of Learning ſhould, yea or could have ſtumbled at this, though the <hi>Name</hi> whereby they are deſigned ſhould import no ſlender <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Prerogative,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, as if the Earth could not ſufficiently furniſh us <hi>titles</hi> of Honour to dignifie that <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Calling,</hi> accordingly, wee finde the Heavens ſought unto, to afford according <hi>Titles,</hi> to ſet forth the high &amp; ſurpaſſing great dignity of that ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and honourable an <hi>Miniſtration,</hi> and ſo ennobled by the bleſſed TRINITY. IT is to be wiſhed, as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaieth well on that they are called <hi>Angeli Domini exercituu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Mal. 2.7. <hi>ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitatem ſervarent in nomine, quam explent in operatione;</hi> yea, <hi>et è converſo, ut quam dignitatem obtinent in nomine, explerent in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione, Numero, ut nomina rebus reſponderent ſuis, et res nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> If we ſhould be pleaſed to prove idle, &amp; ſeek out any lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Pride</hi> in vocables, we might arceſſe their <hi>Preſbyters</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Seniores,</hi> of no leſſe <hi>arrogancy,</hi> &amp; ſo call their divine and ſo much cryed up office of <hi>Elderſhip</hi> in queſtion, which were a piacular ſin: for doeth not the <hi>French</hi> word <hi>Seigneurs,</hi> as if ye ſhould ſay, <hi>Senieurs,</hi> flow from that of <hi>Seniores</hi> nay, and <hi>Senato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> too? but this is but an idle <hi>Logomachy</hi> or vaine conteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout words. But this ſhews forth to the full, as their hate and averſation of the <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>Office,</hi> ſo their beſt poore willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to beare out their point, and roote out the <hi>Order.</hi> If this were ſafe and ſure argumenting, Why might we not no leſſe juſtly cry out againſt the dignity of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> under Chriſts Kingdome, where we are ſaid in common to be made in Him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, into a Royall <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> wher every word ſerves to advance the ſurpaſſing great dignity of our <hi>Condition</hi> under the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> above that under the <hi>Law.</hi> IT wonders me not a little, How that theſe men, who bowed the knee to <hi>Independency,</hi> and proved active and inſtrumentall to bring in a <hi>Paritie</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> as in <hi>Church,</hi> grudged not, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt the uſurped name of a <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> ſince that the Prophet <hi>Iſai.</hi> fore-prophecying of Chriſts <hi>Kingdom, Iſ.</hi> 32. from the beginning, may juſtly ſeeme to vindicate this <hi>Title</hi> to that Man Chriſt, Who is both GOD and Man, and ſo can only prove <hi>an hiding place from the winde, &amp; a covert fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175721:5"/>tempeſt.</hi> How is it that they ſo deeply forgot themſelves, as ſhuning <hi>Charybdis,</hi> they ſhould ſo willingly, as willfully caſt themſelves into <hi>Scylla,</hi> &amp; eſclave themſelves to a farre higher and harder <hi>dependency:</hi> where their leaſt <hi>finger</hi> proved bigger, then were their Fathers <hi>loynes? Certes</hi> me thinks it no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That men, who made it no ſcruple or conſcience, to caſt off their <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LER,</hi> whom GOD had ſet over them, Their juſt Titular <hi>KING,</hi> though GOD Himſelf to dignify the Office of Kings, is pleaſed to impart to them, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with them His <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> by an <hi>Ego dixi dij eſtis,</hi> I have ſaid, yee are gods, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82.6. That they bearing His <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Superſcription,</hi> as it were, might labour to be anſwerable to their <hi>Prototypon,</hi> and ſo ſtrive to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Images of GOD, <hi>in ipſo judicandi munere,</hi> in their due ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> I ſay, I can think it no wonder, That theſe who ſcrupled not, or made the leaſt conſcience to make ſuch an alteration in <hi>State,</hi> ſhould not ſtand on this, to baniſh all order in <hi>Church:</hi> and ſo bring in confuſion in both. Truely theſe ſo grave and learned <hi>Divines</hi> and pious <hi>Reformers,</hi> arceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the bare and naked <hi>Name,</hi> grounds and reaſons to infirme the <hi>Office,</hi> may not without juſt cauſe ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble that <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> who could <hi>Mirifice res exiguas verbis amplificare,</hi> wonderfully amplifie ſmall matters with hye words, whom <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> thought no more commendable for it, then the <hi>Shoe-maker,</hi> who ſhould make great ſhoes for little feet. Thus you ſee, That this is no <hi>verdict</hi> or true <hi>ſaying,</hi> but a <hi>falſe-dict</hi> or <hi>falſe-ſaying,</hi> that the name or appellation of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> ſavours of <hi>Pride</hi> &amp; <hi>arrogancy.</hi> I pray you <hi>num</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quae</hi> Bezae <hi>perplacet appellatio, caret omni ſuperci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> ſtands this <hi>Compellation</hi> voide and free of all <hi>pride?</hi> yea and wheras the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> calls himſelf <hi>ſervum ſervorum;</hi> doth this impaire his <hi>pride,</hi> and not rather augment and increaſe his deepe <hi>hypocriſie?</hi> Is not this ſacred and venerable <hi>Title</hi> aſcribed to Chriſt Himſelf in <hi>ſcripture?</hi> Is not Hee called, <hi>The ſhep-herd and Biſhop of our ſoules?</hi> Nay, may we not upon the ſame ground, <hi>unicâ liturâ,</hi> expunge <hi>Apoſtleſhip:</hi> as that which is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175721:6"/>ſtylled by the Holy Ghoſt <hi>Epiſcope</hi> or <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> thus <hi>Act.</hi> 1.20. whereas <hi>Matthias</hi> is ſuffected in <hi>Judas</hi> his roome, It is ſaid, <hi>Et Epiſcopatum ejus accipiat alter, And his Biſhoprick let another take.</hi> Where, by the way, obſerve; That the word in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is evill rendred in our Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Communibus ſuffragiis allectus eſt:</hi> for the Apoſtles were not by <hi>Election,</hi> but <hi>by Christs immediat deſignation;</hi> And ſo it is better rendred in our vulgar language, <hi>Annumeratus eſt,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> calculus, <hi>And he was numbred with the eleven A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> Act. 1.26. If any ſhould except here, That this Charge <hi>ſortitò ei obtigit,</hi> befell him by <hi>Lot,</hi> IT is eaſily replyed, That the <hi>dispoſition</hi> of the <hi>Lot</hi> is of GOD, and ſo this proves nothing prejudiciall to his immediat and extraordinary CALL. Thus <hi>Non eſt faſtus in nomenclaturâ,</hi> there may well be <hi>in stomach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> veſtro faſtidium;</hi> Nay, and though this <hi>Name</hi> be uſurped with our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> this bereaves not us of our juſt right: for wee cannot loſſe our juſt <hi>title</hi> or <hi>claime</hi> to things, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, That they are abuſed to <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> for I pray you, What is ſo holy, which may not be abuſed to <hi>ſuperſtition?</hi> Now the <hi>abuſe</hi> of a thing, as it taks not away, ſo can it not defraud us of the lawfull <hi>vſe</hi> of it; for elſe <hi>Exſcindenda eſſent nobis vites,</hi> and wee ſhould take out of the Firmament <hi>duo illa Luminaria magna. CHRIST</hi> made vſe in His very firſt <hi>Miracle,</hi> of turning <hi>water</hi> into <hi>wine,</hi> of the veſſels uſed in the jewiſh <hi>Purificatian; Paul</hi> ſailled in a Shipe carrying the badge of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux;</hi> Nay, &amp; our ſtrickeſt <hi>Reformers</hi> preach in <hi>Temples</hi> bearing the <hi>names</hi> of forged and doxaſtick <hi>ſaints</hi> in the popiſh <hi>Legendory.</hi> I beleeve, There is no little diſtance twixt theſe two, to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate, emprunt or borrow a thing from <hi>ſuperstition;</hi> and to vindicate it from <hi>ſuperstition. Magnum hîc</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, lacuna, diſſidium.</hi> Now <hi>Popedome</hi> gave not the ſource or originall to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> but oweth it cadence or deſcent to it. For <hi>Cloſure,</hi> I would gladly learne; If the name of <hi>Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> which is a name of mans impoſition, did ſavour of leſſe <hi>Pride,</hi> yea and wherin ſtood his power or proſtaſy leſſe. Now this ſort of <hi>government</hi> obtained and found place, at our firſt <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175721:6"/>
            <p>Now to come more presſly to the <hi>Point;</hi> The ſecond <hi>Quaere</hi> ſhall bee this; If <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be <hi>Inſtitutionis dominicae,</hi> or barely <hi>dispoſitionis eccleſiaſticae,</hi> of Divine inſtitution, or of meer Eccleſiaſticall diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> having called the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to MILETUS, <hi>Hee exhorts them to take heed unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to all the flock, over the which the Holy Ghoſt had made them Overſeers,</hi> (where the word in the originall is, <hi>Epiſcopos</hi>) to feed the <hi>Church</hi> of God, which Hee had purchaſed with His own Bloud: Now I beleeve, That <hi>Praefectura Spiritus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> cannot be denied to ſtand <hi>Ordinatio,</hi> or <hi>Inſtitutio Divina,</hi> a Divine Ordinance and Inſtitution. If any ſhould except here, That this <hi>Name</hi> ſtands common to theſe our gregary <hi>Laik-Elders</hi> brought on our <hi>ſtage</hi> to day; There be two maine <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> militating here to the contrary: For firſt, The <hi>Charge</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them or entruſted them, ſciz. <hi>Paſcere gregem,</hi> to feed the flock, evinceth the contrarie, for <hi>Hi tondent et diglubunt.</hi> 2. This <hi>Charge</hi> is ſaid, to have been entruſted or committed to them, by the Holy Ghoſt, which both are here wanting with our temporary, yea well oft extemporary <hi>Elders.</hi> Againe, The ſame Apoſtle <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. Having directed his <hi>ſalutation to all the Saints in Christ Jeſus</hi> in common, ſubjoines, <hi>with the Biſhops and Deacons;</hi> Wherupon <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> having poſed the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, wherfore he had left no place <hi>intermedio Tagmati Preſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terorum?</hi> Replyes ſtraight, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe there is no diſtance or difference here: For, ſayeth hee, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame things are competent to the one, which to the other: for the <hi>Order</hi> ſtands but one and the ſame, admitting onely a diſparitie of <hi>degree</hi> in the <hi>Order.</hi> Who ſeeth not, except a <hi>Borne blind,</hi> That if we ſhall deny <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy,</hi> to ſtand of divine <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> we ſhall <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ liturâ</hi> expunge <hi>Preſbyteratum cum Epiſcopaetu,</hi> ELDERSHIP with EPISCOPACY out of this <hi>Claſſe,</hi> and ſo to deny it to ſtand of divine <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> which with our zealous moderne <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> to day were <hi>grande nefas, et plus quam morte piandum.</hi> Nay
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175721:7"/>
               <hi>Ex promiſcuo uſu vocabulorum, non ſtatim rectè infertur paritas Miniſtrorum:</hi> for the promiſcuous uſe of a <hi>word,</hi> doeth not alwayes ſtraight ſubinferre with it, the indiſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a <hi>thing.</hi> Wee would heed well in this Argument, to remember that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> may be conſidered two wayes, either in the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract,</hi> as an <hi>Order,</hi> or in the <hi>Concret,</hi> as <hi>exerced by men in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Now thought it ſhould not have been rightly here exerced and adminiſtred by theſe, but that they ſhould have ſingularly appropriated to themſelves ſomthings which ſtood co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to <hi>Preſbytries</hi> with them, This could not nor cannot infirme the <hi>Office:</hi> for perſonall <hi>infirmities</hi> beare no aſperſion upon the <hi>Calling;</hi> What <hi>Calling</hi> ſtands ſo holy, which may not ſuffer <hi>abuſe?</hi> I beleeve, That our holy and zealous <hi>Diſciplinarians</hi> cannot, yea dare not take upon them to juſtifie all their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent <hi>actings</hi> whether in <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Church:</hi> for do we not heare daylie of their <hi>Retractations</hi> and <hi>Retro-gradations</hi> in both. <hi>In multis labimur omnes,</hi> no place here for <hi>perfection;</hi> wee muſt not confound <hi>viam cum patria,</hi> or e converſo. Againe, <hi>1. Cor.</hi> 12.28.29. <hi>Liquido cernere est imparitatem Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrorum.</hi> Againe the ſame Apoſtle 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; calleth this a <hi>verdict</hi> or <hi>true ſaying,</hi> That <hi>If a man deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſireth a good work.</hi> yea and layes down his required <hi>qualification;</hi> as ſemblably <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. which could not hold true, if <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſtood an unlawfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable <hi>Office</hi> in Church. But leſt any ſhould or could fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence inferre an <hi>Iſotomy</hi> or <hi>Homotomy,</hi> an equality of <hi>Honour</hi> from off of the communion of <hi>Names;</hi> you are to take heed well in this argument, that from <hi>aque</hi> ad <hi>aquale,</hi> the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, ſtands inconſequent: for under the LAW, <hi>Sacerdotiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> was but one and the ſame, they were all <hi>aquè Sacerdotes,</hi> &amp; yet there ceaſed not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence to be a diſparitie of <hi>degree</hi> in one &amp; the ſame <hi>Order:</hi> for the High-Prieſt <hi>prae cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris eminebat,</hi> he emine above the reſt, and ſo from that legall <hi>oeconomy</hi> this <hi>Order</hi> may be arceſſed and inſtructed. Againe leſt there ſhould be any place left here for <hi>exception;</hi> That from the <hi>Law,</hi> to the <hi>Goſpell</hi> it ſhould prove inconſequentiall; This is no leſſe conſencaneous &amp; agreable with the Evangelicall <hi>oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175721:7"/>or <hi>dispenſation</hi> under the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> forwheras <hi>CHRIST aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up on high, Hee gave ſome to be Apoſtles, &amp; ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangelists, and ſome pastours and teachers.</hi> Epheſ. 4.11. where there cannot be denied to have been a diſparity of <hi>degree.</hi> but leſt there ſhould be any place here left for exceprio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that this onely ſerves to militate here, and to inſtruct a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and diſparitie of <hi>degree</hi> twixt the ſeverall <hi>Claſſes,</hi> but can make nothing to inſtruct a diſparitie of <hi>degree</hi> amongſt thoſe of one and the ſame <hi>Claſſe.</hi> I would poſe him here, How is it, that amongſt the very Apoſtles ſome are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Inſignes, ſeeming pillars,</hi> as <hi>James, Cephas</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Gal. 2.9. May not this ſeeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſome <hi>disparitie,</hi> if not <hi>in officio, ſaltem in regimine:</hi> for why may there not be <hi>impares gradus in regimine,</hi> yea, and that <hi>in aequali officio,</hi> to avoide <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>confuſion?</hi> What would <hi>S. Paul</hi> imply, whereas be ſaieth, <hi>That he was nothing inferiour to the very chiefeſt Apoſtles;</hi> for albeit this <hi>paſſage</hi> will not ſtraight ſubinferre, that, beſids the <hi>Twelve Apostles,</hi> there wer others of a ſecondary <hi>rank,</hi> yet it maks the <hi>Argument</hi> ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in that there were amongſt the very <hi>Twelve,</hi> ſome more, ſome leſſe chief; Now <hi>Magis</hi> and <hi>minus,</hi> though they alter not the <hi>spece,</hi> they alter the <hi>degree.</hi> I am not ignorant how ſome except here, That there is a <hi>fallacie</hi> here from the communion of <hi>Names.</hi> But I pray you, doeth communion of <hi>Names,</hi> import and inferre alwayes with it, a communion of <hi>Office</hi> and communion of equality of degree in the <hi>Office,</hi> yea and in the externall regiment too? Doeth it ſtraight follow from hence, That <hi>Peter</hi> calls himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Fellow-Preſbyter,</hi> 1. Pet. 5.1. that he emined not, or had no <hi>prerogative</hi> above theſe whom he thus enſtiled? I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learne (where I promiſe to yeeld my ſelf docil and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) wherefore there may not be an <hi>inequality</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> in government, as there is a <hi>disparitie</hi> acknowledged to be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>gifts?</hi> May there not fall our <hi>abuſes</hi> in theſe, as in that of <hi>Power?</hi> Wherefore is <hi>Timothy</hi> enſtiled <hi>The firſt Biſhop of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians;</hi> yea and <hi>Titus the first Biſhop of the Church of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians?</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:175721:8"/>I know ſome to except here, That the argument can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought preſſing, which is onely taken from the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</hi> Anſw. There be in <hi>Epistles</hi> theſe three; <hi>Inſcriptura, Scriptura</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptura.</hi> Now with what parreſy or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they may challenge <hi>Subſcripturam,</hi> may they not with the ſame <hi>Inſcripturam?</hi> Yea I have heard ſome of the ſtricteſt <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> or <hi>Diſciplinariaens</hi> challenge <hi>Scripturam,</hi> call the whole body of an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> in queſtion, a thing of a well dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, and giving the enemy no ſmall advantage; But I reaſon not ſimply from the <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> but make <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam,</hi> the body of the Epiſtle my <hi>Ground.</hi> How is it, That theſe <hi>Charges</hi> are borne on theſe two, on Timothy <hi>That he lay not on hands ſuddenly on no man,</hi> 1. Tim. 5.22. Yea and that he layes down <hi>Rules</hi> to be obſerved of him in reproving, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2. and on Titus, <hi>That he ſhould ſet in order the things which were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ordaine Elders in every City,</hi> Tit. 1.5.? what belonged this to <hi>Timothy,</hi> if he had no further power then any ordinary or gregary <hi>Preſbyter,</hi> to admitt or receive orderly of accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt <hi>Preſbyters?</hi> But I know ſome to except here, That <hi>Timothy</hi> was an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> and that ſo <hi>Biſhops</hi> cannot from hence acclaime to any intereſt in that his <hi>right.</hi> IT wonders me to ſee men ſo blindly wedded to their own <hi>Notions;</hi> That they cannot but cheriſh them, how unſound ſoever: like to a woman kiſſing and embracing her own <hi>abortion:</hi> for if he ſhal turne an <hi>Evangelist</hi> from hence, that he is bidden <hi>Do the work of an Evangeliſt,</hi> II. Tim. 4.5. Why may we not from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gener warrant tranſhape him into an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> In that <hi>S. Paul</hi> willeth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to receive him ſo, <hi>as that he may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare,</hi> and the reaſon is ſubjoined, <hi>Becauſe that he wrought the work of the Lord, as he did,</hi> 1. Cor. 16.10. Thus <hi>Nihil hîc niſi ſcopae diſſolutae.</hi> I pray you, was <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> a part <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarii muneris,</hi> of an extraordinary <hi>Chaerge? Certes,</hi> thus it ſhould ceaſe to have any place or vſe with us to day, &amp; expire with the perſons of an extraordinary <hi>Call.</hi> Againe, How do theſe <hi>Seers</hi> ſo deeply forget themſelves here? whereas they ſtraight abaſe and degrade him, redact him into the claſſe &amp;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175721:8"/>ranke of ordinary and gregary <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> from off of that paſſage 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. where he is exhorted by PAUL, <hi>Not to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the gift that was in him, which was given him by prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the Preſbytrie.</hi> Which cannot be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> or of <hi>one</hi> extraordinarly called: Now <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax oportet ſit ſui ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per memor,</hi> A liar would have a good memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Nay, and how do they againe forget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves ſo deeply, as to argue from off of this paſſage, ſince <hi>Paul</hi> reſtraines this, <hi>to the laying on of his own hands,</hi> II. Tim. 1.6.? Nay and ſome of the learned take <hi>Preſbyterium, pro preſbyteratu,</hi> for the <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Office</hi> it ſelf, and not for a <hi>Colledge</hi> or <hi>Society</hi> of meere <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Now as I have ſaid, <hi>Epiſcopatus</hi> and <hi>Presbyteratus,</hi> ſtand but <hi>unum et idem Tagma,</hi> admitting onely a diſparity of degree in the <hi>Order;</hi> Alwiſe I would learne of theſe <hi>Seraphick</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned Doctours,</hi> Wherefore it is, That ſeing in the Church of the <hi>Cretians</hi> there were more <hi>Presbyters;</hi> This is ſingularly recommended to <hi>Titus,</hi> to <hi>ordaine Elders in every City, to ſet in order the things that were left undone, to reject an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition?</hi> Why is this priviledge ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie indulted and permitted to Timothy and Titus, <hi>Presbyteros conſtituere vel exauctorare,</hi> if any gregary presbyter had a like power with them? For as I beleeve, <hi>par in parem non habet po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall we deferre no reſpect to the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of this cuſtome in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, in, &amp; throughout the whole 4 <hi>Patriarchicall</hi> ſeas or ſeats, <hi>Hieroſolymitana, Antiochena, Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ana et Alexandrina.</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> deduceth well the <hi>ſeries</hi> or <hi>line</hi> of the perpetuated ſucceſſion of <hi>Biſhops</hi> to his times, which evidenceth that this ſort of government obtained well timeouſly in the Church, from the very dayes of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> Shall we deferre nothing to the teſtimony of that famous Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> (Wherunto, I beleeve all our purer Moderne Councels in theſe our dayes of ſo bleſſed and glorious, ſo much cryed up work of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> cannot be parelleled or ſtand worthie to come in competition) which affirmeth this Government not to be <hi>Nova Inſtitutionis, ſed antiqui moris,</hi> of new Inſtitution, but of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175721:9"/>ancient cuſtom; Nay, &amp; the ſame Councel decreed, That ther ſhould not be two <hi>Biſhops</hi> in one City, but this change with us to day, is nothing to be admired, to ſee men to contemne, yea condemne all <hi>Antiquity,</hi> who love onely <hi>Novations,</hi> and dote upon <hi>Novelties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobilitat Novitas, quod damnat ſaepe vetuſtas</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could thinke, that ſome reſpect were to be deferred to the teſtimony of piouſly learned <hi>Calvin,</hi> a witneſſe of old with the beſt of this ſtampe of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Diſciplinarians, omni exceptione major.</hi> Now he in the fourth book of his <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions. ſect.</hi> 1. ſets down theſe expreſſe words; <hi>It ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in theſe things to conſider the forme of the old Church, which ſhall repreſent to our eyes, a certaine Image of Gods Inſtitution: for although the Biſhops of theſe tims did ſet forth many Canons, wherin they ſeemed to expreſſe more, then was expreſſed in holy Scripture, yet they with ſuch heedfulneſſe framed all their order, after the onely rule of Gods Word; that a man may eaſiſly ſee, in this behalfe; that they had nothing diſſagreeing from Gods Word.</hi> And ſtraight after ſubjoines; <hi>Thaet out of a ſincere zeale they endeavoured to preſerve Gods Inſtitution, and that they ſwarved not much from it.</hi> Nay, and ſtraight againe in the 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> he ſubjoines, <hi>That in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City they elected or chooſed out of their own number one Man, to whom they gave ſpecially the title of Biſhop, lest from an equality, as it uſually falls out, diſſentions ſhould grow and ariſe;</hi> I beleeve, That we have found and felt the ſmart of this <hi>trueth,</hi> by ſad &amp; dolefull experience of late amongſt our ſelves. Let our fyerie <hi>Zelots,</hi> theſe ſonnes of <hi>Thunder</hi> ſee to it, <hi>quâ facie, quô fronte, quâ <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quâ audaciâ,</hi> with what <hi>face</hi> or <hi>conſcience,</hi> they could not onely have themſelves: but violently enforced others, to abjure ſimply, this ſo ancient, ſo ſacred, yea and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> as meerly <hi>Anti-Chriſtian:</hi> and ſo out of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith, called for, yea and exacted a blind <hi>obedience.</hi> Now I beleeve, That <hi>ultima fidei analyſis,</hi> the laſt reſolution of faith is, <hi>in Deus dixit:</hi> for <hi>Credere promiſcuè quicquid affirmatur à Praelatis, non opus eſt virilis intelligentiae ſed puerilis inſcitiae.</hi> It fears me not a little, from the fyrie heate, which our Moderne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175721:9"/>
               <hi>Reformers</hi> have ſhewed and kithed in the proſecution of this their ſo much cryed up work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> that if thoſe holy fathera, <hi>S. Auguſtine, S. Ambroſe, S. Cyprian,</hi> nay and all the reſt of that ſtampe, who wer of old holden <hi>Eccleſiae Lumina, Chriſtianae Reipub. Columina;</hi> yea, and thoſe Learned &amp; godlie <hi>Biſhops</hi> in our Neighbour Nation, who ſuffered <hi>Martyr-dome</hi> for bearing teſtimony to Chriſt, and to His Trueth, had lived in theſe our dayes amongſt us; They ſhould have found no more mercy, with, or from them, then did our Moderne <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats,</hi> yea and many honeſt ſuffering <hi>Brethren:</hi> but all ſhould have gone through their firery triall. But to returne, <hi>unde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio quo digreſſus luxuriante calamo;</hi> Wherefore is it I pray you, That <hi>S. Iohn</hi> directs all his <hi>Epiſtles</hi> which he writs to the ſeven Churches in ASIA, <hi>Angelo cujuſque Eccleſiae,</hi> to the Angell of each Church ſingularly? I know that our <hi>Reformers</hi> will not have that to be denied of the reſt, <hi>quod de uno praedicatur,</hi> and that ſo the word <hi>Angell</hi> ſhould be rendred per <hi>Miniſtrum</hi> ſimply, or leſe all the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in common to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deſigned here, and ſo to be taken <hi>Collectively,</hi> and not one particular <hi>Perſon</hi> to be pointed at. But with their leave, Since there were in each of theſe Churches more <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> then one, as may be inſtanced from that of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> This interpretation muſt needs fall of will, which renders the word <hi>per Miniſtrum</hi> in the <hi>ſingular number</hi> onely, for thus it ſhould follow; That there ſhould have been but one <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> in each Church, againe on the other hand, If all the <hi>Prebyters</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſhould, or were here to be underſtood under this <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Angell,</hi> why do we offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to <hi>S. Iohns</hi> words, by the change of the <hi>Number?</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it, that he ſtill directs his ſpeech to <hi>One,</hi> nay and if the ſpeech ſtand directed to the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in common, how could it be cognoſced to whom it were ſingularly thus directed? Againe, If this <hi>One</hi> ſtood not inſtructed with ſome <hi>power</hi> over the reſt, but all in common partooke of alike <hi>Power</hi> with him, how is he thus ſingularly entituled above the reſt? And which is more, How is the <hi>faultineſſe</hi> of all in common, imputed ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175721:10"/>to him? <hi>Marlorat</hi> on the 2 of the <hi>Revel.</hi> jumps here in judgement, whiles he ſayes, moſt pertinently to this purpoſe, <hi>Non populum aggreditur leannes, ſed Principem Cleriuti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum.</hi> Nay, and hitherto <hi>Beza</hi> in his Annotations on the 3 of the <hi>Rev.</hi> rendreth the word <hi>Angelo,</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> quem <hi>oportuit de his rebus imprimis admoneri,</hi> from hence it followes, That this <hi>Angell</hi> had a <hi>Proſtaſie, preſeance, preſidence</hi> and <hi>prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence</hi> above his <hi>Fellow-Miniſters;</hi> But I heare ſome replying here, That if this <hi>Proſtaſie</hi> was of this kind, it was only over the <hi>Common flock,</hi> and not of power and authority over his <hi>Fellow-Miniſters.</hi> Anſw. <hi>Dato, non conceſſo,</hi> giving, but not granting; That this <hi>Proſtaſie</hi> or <hi>preſeance</hi> were only over the <hi>Flock,</hi> yet it remains, That it was a proſtaſie of <hi>Power,</hi> elſe how could he have excerced any Authority over them; Nay but he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to exerce it, even againſt <hi>Fellow-Miniſters</hi> or preaching <hi>Elders,</hi> yea, and is commended from hence, that he tooke or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with them, <hi>Who called themſelves Apostles, but were not, &amp; found them liars.</hi> Revel. 2.2. I heare againe ſome excepting againſt this <hi>Trueth,</hi> though ſo clearly and fully vindicated and aſſerted, from off of theſe paſſages, <hi>Math.</hi> 20.25.26.27. and I. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.3. Where Chriſt prohibits his Apoſtles to exerce ſuch <hi>Dominion</hi> as did <hi>Reges terrae</hi> or <hi>Magnates,</hi> and where <hi>Peter</hi> warnes the <hi>Elders ſo to feed the flock of God, as not domineiring over the Lords inheritance: but proving enſamples to the flock.</hi> Now in both theſe there is a plaine fallacie, <hi>à mo do rei ad rem,</hi> from the manner, to the matter; Now I beleeve, that the different manner of a thing, is ſo far from the overthrowing or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of the thing it ſelf, that on the contrary, <hi>Ponit et ſubin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert,</hi> it puts &amp; ſubinferres it, and ſo both, Chriſt &amp; <hi>S. Peter</hi> take not away ſimply all <hi>power</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but ſuch a modalized one, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>deſpoticall, herill</hi> or <hi>civill power,</hi> but not <hi>Paternall</hi> &amp; <hi>Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</hi> Doth not the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> I. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. laſt verſ. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, <hi>That all things be done in the Church decently, and in order.</hi> Now I beleeve, that <hi>Order</hi> which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls it, ſecluds a parity, for what elſe is ORDER, <hi>Quàm parium impariumque, ſua cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuens
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175721:10"/>loca, dispoſitio?</hi> and ſo wher all ſtands alike in dignity &amp; power, <hi>ibi ordints, decori ne umbra quidem,</hi> there can be no ſhaddow of <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Comlineſſe:</hi> from whence it is conſequentiall, That if we take away imparity, <hi>una et eadem opera omnem ordinem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſacros Evangelii Miniſtros turbatum et everſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibimus;</hi> we ſhall overturne all order, and baniſh it the Church. I heare ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying here, That it cannot be denied, that <hi>Presbyters</hi> for a time did governe ſome Churches, <hi>pariauthoritate et communi Conſilio.</hi> Anſ. This derogats nothing from <hi>Epiſcopall dignity,</hi> nor proves prejudiciall to it, but rather confirmes the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Epiſcopall <hi>Charge,</hi> in that this ſort of <hi>Regiment</hi> even in the very Apoſtles dayes and times, <hi>perpetuiis diſſidiis Eceleſias dilaceravit,</hi> did rent the Church by perpetuall diſſentions. I deny not with <hi>S. Hierome, Epiſcopos presbyteris majores, conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine magis, quam Dominica Inſtitutionis veritate:</hi> but this is rightly to be underſtood, ſciz. as to the appropriation of the <hi>Tule</hi> to one above another: for it was <hi>Conſuetudo Eccleſiae,</hi> the cuſtome of the Church that made the <hi>title</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> greater, then that of a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> &amp; not any Dominicall or Apoſtolicall diſpoſition or conſtitution, &amp; ſo his words ar to be underſtood by accommodation and reſtraint to his own times, and ſo of that Authority, which <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſo called obtained then over <hi>Presbyters.</hi> Alwiſe for the leaſt, it is cleare and evident from hence, That <hi>S. Hierome</hi> did not averſe an <hi>imparitie</hi> in Church, yea, and giving, though not granting, That this imparity or diverſitie of <hi>degrees</hi> amongſt the Miniſters of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is not founded or grounded upon any expreſſe warrant of Chriſt in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> yet this ſo ancient a practiſe taking its ſource &amp; beginning from the very <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and having continued ſo conſtantly ſince in the Chriſtian Church, may ſtand for a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> to us, and may ſerve us for a <hi>Directory</hi> for the regulation of our comportment and approbation of ſo ancient a cuſtome and practiſe, and not of new <hi>Inſtitution.</hi> IT is not unknown how <hi>Aeri</hi>ꝰ was condemned of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> for condemning of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy;</hi> There be many <hi>Aerians</hi> with us to day, both for <hi>Name</hi> &amp; <hi>matter,</hi> if it were lawfull <hi>ab eventu facta putare,</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrue of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175721:11"/>things from their <hi>events,</hi> I might mak bold here, to referre the <hi>matter,</hi> not only to indifferent <hi>Arbiters,</hi> but to the deciſion of the moſt ſtrict <hi>Diſciplinarians,</hi> whether the <hi>Church</hi> or trueth of <hi>Religion</hi> proſpered or flowriſhed more, under that <hi>Prelaticall</hi> Government, as ſome are pleaſed thus odiouſly to traduce it. then under this late <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> &amp; under which of theſe two, the <hi>Church</hi> in her juſt <hi>liberties</hi> ſtood more or leſſe eclipſed; I may boldly averre, <hi>That as Aarons rod budded, bloſſomed and bore rype Almonds, whereas all the rest of the rods of the twelve Princes of Iſraell were blasted:</hi> ſo under <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> government the <hi>Trueth</hi> was maintained in greater <hi>purity;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> enjoyed farre greater <hi>Liberties freedome</hi> &amp; <hi>Priviledges,</hi> then under this new coyned and forged <hi>Presbyteriall:</hi> for under that <hi>facta multa acceſſio credentium Eccleſiae,</hi> There was made a great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of <hi>Beleevers</hi> to the Church: But alas under this no leſſe <hi>deceſſion,</hi> as was wel timouſly fore-prophecyed by a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>Prelate,</hi> at the firſt rearing up of this ſo great, ſo glorious cryed up worke of <hi>Reformation.</hi> And if any acceſſion bee made, it is <hi>credendorum,</hi> and not <hi>Credentium,</hi> for theſe men ſcruple not <hi>fidei articulos condere et ſolvere,</hi> as they durſt make bold to turne <hi>Christi documentum,</hi> into <hi>Nocumentum:</hi> and blaſphemouſly to call the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> a Nocent <hi>Ceremony;</hi> yea, and to account the recitall of it at ſervice, a Note of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy;</hi> I may no leſſe boldly averre now, that many with us to day both in <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church, Quà ibatur cuntes,</hi> but <hi>quà eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem non inquirentes,</hi> from off of this ſo ſad and dolefull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the bitter fruits of this lamentable <hi>Change</hi> and <hi>altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> as <hi>Church,</hi> their Government would be glad to run back <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, et <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſubmitte their necks with all cheerfulneſſe to thoſe yokes of <hi>woode,</hi> under the which they were well gently preſſed under that Government in both, that they might ſhake themſelves looſe and free of theſe of <hi>Iron:</hi> lying ſo heavily on them, under theſe new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced ones. <hi>Veritas eſt filia temporis;</hi> for a parity in <hi>Church,</hi> hath brought on and in, a parity in <hi>State;</hi> and ſo a lamentable and deplorable <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>diſorder</hi> in both. Thus no wonder
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175721:11"/>That KING <hi>JAMES</hi> of bleſſed Memory, uſed this ordinary expreſſion, <hi>No Biſhop, no KING:</hi> for <hi>Quàm benè convenium, mutuas ſibi praeſtant operas, et conſpirant amice.</hi> If I durſt make bold here, I would interpone my poor and meane, but well meaning <hi>advice</hi> in this buſſines, which ſhortly take it thus; That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> may remaine and be keeped on foot, the <hi>Abuſe</hi> onely being removed and taken away, which might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily have at firſt, compoſed the <hi>Contest;</hi> viz. That whereas there ſhall happen or fall out any <hi>vacancy</hi> in an Epiſcopall <hi>ſea</hi> or <hi>ſeat;</hi> That the <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Diocy</hi> may fullie conveene themſelves, and condeſcend upon ſome ſelected <hi>Ones</hi> out of their Number, of beſt <hi>abilities</hi> for a due acquitall in ſo eminent a <hi>Miniſtration,</hi> and give in theſe to the Supreame <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in a <hi>Lite</hi> or <hi>Liſt,</hi> granting him <hi>Conge de lire,</hi> or Liberty of <hi>Election:</hi> as <hi>Penes quem ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit prae eſſe externo Regimini.</hi> Whoſe ſolely it is to manage the externall Regiment of the Church, ſtanding with <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the Great, <hi>Epiſcopus ad extra;</hi> and that ſuch a <hi>One</hi> be thus praefected over the reſt, for the preſervation of good <hi>Order,</hi> and keeping all in a right <hi>frame,</hi> and ſhuning of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> upon an confuſed parity; <hi>Ad Culpam</hi> onely, And not <hi>ad vitam,</hi> even in caſe of abuſe of his <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>Tyranny:</hi> for <hi>Forma Apoſtolica haec eſt, dominatio interdicitur, indicitur Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio;</hi> The ſpirits of the <hi>Prophets</hi> ſtand ſubject to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and ſo their <hi>Power</hi> ſtanding but a delegated one, upon <hi>abuſe</hi> may ſuffer and admit a warrantable <hi>repetition.</hi> If this <hi>Courſe</hi> had been taken, or preſented by our violent <hi>Reformers</hi> to our ſacred and dread SOVERAIGN, I am aſſured that ſuch wofull <hi>diſorders</hi> had not fallen out in <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> Who may not ſee, except a <hi>Born-blind,</hi> the dolefull <hi>ſequels?</hi> yea I may boldly now ſay, upon ſad and lamentable experience (which <hi>Aſſeveration</hi> at the firſt ſetting on foot of this great &amp; glorious work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſtood <hi>grande uefas, et plus quàm morte piandum</hi>) effects of an arbitrary government in <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Church:</hi> For <hi>Let there be no King in Iſrael, and then every man ſhall do what ſeemeth good in his own eyes,</hi> as you may ſee in the latter chap. of the <hi>Judges</hi> paſſim. Nay, and let <hi>Moſes</hi> the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175721:12"/>
               <hi>Judge</hi> ſubduce himſelf to the <hi>Mount</hi> for the leaſt ſpace, and then the whole people, <hi>etiam Aarone duce,</hi> ſhall fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in common to <hi>Idolatry.</hi> I beleeve we may learne a better <hi>After-wit</hi> in both, having bought it by dolefull experience at the higheſt rate.</p>
            <p>By your leave, That I may ſpeak ſomewhat <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or en paſſant of this new modalized <hi>Presbyteriall Government;</hi> I would gladly underſtand, on what <hi>Mount</hi> they have ſeen the <hi>Patern,</hi> after the which they have effigia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, exaſciated, edolated and reared up this ſtructure of this <hi>Preſbyteriall Government,</hi> conſiſting or made up of ſuch ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients or conſtitutives, viz. of two ſorts of <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> RULING and LABOURING, nay, and wherefore ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as their <hi>buſſineſſe</hi> in hand called for, the number of the RU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING was doubled, <hi>Quò certaretur numero, praevalerent confuſo boatu,</hi> for <hi>Suffragia numerabantur, non ponderabantur (majori parte vincente ſaniorem,</hi> It fears me, it was not mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> for I cannot thinke that Chriſt frequented but the leaſt this <hi>Mount,</hi> farre leſſe that Hee was here transfigured, Hee may well perhaps have been disfigured. Sure I am it is the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type</hi> it ſelf: for ſeing that the <hi>Divines</hi> agree in common that there be <hi>Two Claſſes</hi> onely of ſtanding <hi>Officers</hi> in the Church under the Goſpel, <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Presbyters,</hi> which ſtand but one and the ſame order, and <hi>Deacons.</hi> I would learne upon what warrantable grounds, they have brought upon our <hi>stage</hi> to day, this third <hi>Claſſe</hi> or <hi>Ranke</hi> of RULING or LAIK <hi>Elders,</hi> as they are pleaſed to baptize them, a <hi>spece</hi> of <hi>Presbyters</hi> unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Gods Word, yea unknown to all <hi>Antiquity.</hi> IT is not unknown what <hi>Tertullian</hi> diſproved in his time, <hi>Hodie Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, cras Laicus,</hi> I beleeve with the Apoſtle, That it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Manum huic aratro admotam dimovere,</hi> to take back the hand from this <hi>Plough.</hi> Thus <hi>Anniculi nostri</hi> or <hi>Biennales Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri</hi> were unknown and unheard of in theſe times, far more theſe extemporary <hi>Elders,</hi> whereof uſe was well oft made, as the neceſſity of their <hi>Affairs</hi> required. Whereas they were pretended to have been brought in, for the better ordering of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175721:12"/>Gods <hi>Houſe,</hi> The event hath proven the contrary, that they wrought no ſmall <hi>Diſorder</hi> both in <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church;</hi> And whereas they were pretended to have been brought in vſe on our <hi>stage</hi> with <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> to have ſuſtented and ſtayed up <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands, whiles going about a praying, and ſo for the good and help of the labouring <hi>Presbyters</hi> to ſtrengthen their hands, the <hi>ſequel</hi> hath proven, that there was no vſe made of them, but to weaken the hands of the ableſt <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> yea to work their <hi>degradation,</hi> if they did not prove active and inſtrumentall to promove the glory of their <hi>Worke,</hi> and ſhould happen to ſhew the leaſt <hi>diſſaffection</hi> to the <hi>Worke</hi> in hand. Who is ſo blind, that hee may not clearly ſee from bought experience, That they are ſo farre from being worthy to <hi>carry an Ephod before the Lord,</hi> that they are not worthy with the <hi>Gaboanites, to hew wood, and draw water for the uſe of the Lords Altar?</hi> Since <hi>Antiquity</hi> diſclaimes them, and will not owne them, let us come to the <hi>Word</hi> of GOD the ſafeſt and ſureſt <hi>Directory</hi> for the finding out of Miniſteriall <hi>Offices</hi> or <hi>Charges:</hi> Now we finde <hi>neque volam neque veſtigium,</hi> no trace of them here at all, for if we ſhall be pleaſed to look to the firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Deacons,</hi> Act. 6. or to the <hi>Canons</hi> whereunto this <hi>spece</hi> of <hi>Miniſtry</hi> ought to be appended and exacted, <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 3. We ſhall finde them not to have ſo much as any colourable <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> from hence, whether for manner of <hi>Qualification,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> and <hi>Ordination.</hi> As to the firſt, <hi>They behoved to be men of good and honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt, and of wiſedome, men having the Mysterie of faith in a good Conſcience;</hi> who might have been received to that <hi>Charge,</hi> admitted to that <hi>Miniſtery;</hi> Now with us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in hoc Collegium cooptantur, hoc munere veſtiuntur, hoc titulo gaudent, ornantur,</hi> ſome promiſcuouſly of the very <hi>dreggs</hi> of the People, nay, and ſome ſtigmatized ones, <hi>Carbone notati</hi> moſt diſſolute, and licentious <hi>Livers</hi> have proven readieſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into this wholeſome <hi>Incorporation:</hi> as who durſt not but approve their beſt ſubſervencie to their <hi>Luſtfulneſſe.</hi> As to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175721:13"/>the 2. They were inveſted in this <hi>Charge, by prayer and impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands. Quae omnia hîc deſiderantur,</hi> which are all here wanting with our moderne <hi>Elders;</hi> Nay, and this was not a viciſſitudinary or temporary <hi>Charge</hi> as this is with us, but they that had miniſtred well, and acquitted themſelves in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> acquired and purchaſed to themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>praeclarum gradum,</hi> a faire and further <hi>degree,</hi> which <hi>S. Nazianzen</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ceu</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I am not ignorant that ſome, yea, and theſe not unlearned too, will have them to ſtand of a divine <hi>generation,</hi> and hitherto arceſſe their <hi>Pedegree, Cadence</hi> or <hi>Deſcent</hi> from off of that paſſage of ſcripture <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 5.17. where, <hi>The Elders that rule well, are commanded to be had in double honour, but especially</hi> (ſay they) <hi>theſe who labour in Word &amp; Doctrine;</hi> But it fears mee, if wee will be pleaſed to eye this <hi>Text</hi> more nearly and narrowly, we ſhall finde this to be but a gloſſe of <hi>Orleans</hi> deſtroying the <hi>Text,</hi> as may evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare from theſe a few enſuing <hi>Reaſons. First,</hi> The Apoſtle is not claſſing or diſtinguiſhing Elders, in <hi>Ruling</hi> and <hi>Labouring Elders in word and doctrine,</hi> for thus both ſhould ſtand <hi>worthy of double honour,</hi> though mainely that the <hi>Labouring</hi> do merite or challenge this <hi>respect.</hi> But hee defines well <hi>Ruling Elders</hi> to ſtand and be ſuch, who painfully <hi>labour ad ſudorem pulvereum</hi> (which the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>pulvis,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) and thus the Apoſtle ſets not down two ſeverall <hi>Claſſes</hi> or <hi>ranks</hi> of them.
<list>
                  <item>2. Doth not the annexed or ſubjoined <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> wherfore this <hi>honour</hi> is averred to ſtand due, clearly evict this to the full, viz. <hi>That wee ſhould not muzle the ox that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the Corne; and that the Labourer is worthy of his hyre or wages?</hi> Now are theſe your <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> brought on your <hi>ſtage,</hi> of the number of theſe <hi>Oxen, that tread out the Corne?</hi> You confeſſe them not to be of the Cenſe of theſe <hi>Labourers,</hi> elſe why do yee contra-diſtinguiſh them.</item>
                  <item>3. If yee will needs have a diſtinction or claſſing here of <hi>Preſbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> Lo it muſt needs be here, <hi>Inter Magis</hi> et <hi>Minus laborantes.</hi> The
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175721:13"/>more, or leſſe painfull <hi>Labourers;</hi> Now <hi>Magis</hi> et <hi>Minus, More</hi> or <hi>Leſſe,</hi> as they ſpeak in <hi>Schooles, non mutant speciem ſed gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> they change not nor alter not the <hi>spece,</hi> but the <hi>degree</hi> onely.</item>
                  <item>4. IT is not unknown that ſome, yea, and not unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too, by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> underſtand <hi>ſtipendîum.</hi> wages or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. I pray you then as yee divide the <hi>Province</hi> or <hi>Task,</hi> why will yee not ſuffer and admit a diviſion or partage in the <hi>Wages</hi> or <hi>Reward.</hi> IT fears me, and that well juſtly too, That in this caſe, the ſtricteſt of you would not prove deficient to themſelves, but would endeavour themſelves to finde out a new <hi>gloſſe</hi> on the <hi>words,</hi> and make up a new <hi>Commentary;</hi> as I am no leſſe aſſured on the other hand, That theſe our well <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> with us to day, would be no leſſe ready to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime to their right and intereſt in this <hi>Reward,</hi> if they ſhould finde any ſure or firme <hi>baſis</hi> whereupon to ground their <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</hi> and <hi>Claim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Some no ſlenderly expert in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall language averre, That after <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> there would be required the adverſative particle <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to import a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie <hi>distinction.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. Some no leſſe expert in this original language, arceſſe ſome ground of reaſon from off of the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents</hi> and grammaticall <hi>ſpirits,</hi> to infirme and weaken this <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction</hi> or <hi>claſſing.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> But I love not to ſtraine <hi>apiculations</hi> in gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>matications. Thus this very paſſage, wherin <hi>tantum ponunt praeſidij,</hi> they place the full force and ſtrength of their CAUSE, <hi>petit jugulum cauſae,</hi> it cuts the throat of their <hi>Cauſe;</hi> and ſo <hi>unde illi vitam, nos mortem.</hi> This poor wandering <hi>Levite</hi> muſt harbour and reſt with the <hi>Godly Party</hi> forſooth; finding no where elſe in <hi>Heaven</hi> or upon <hi>Earth</hi> an harbouring or ſhelte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring place. No wonder that ſuch a <hi>Heterogenious body,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted of ſuch diſſimilary parts ſhould ſuffer ſuch a ſudden <hi>diſſolution.</hi> Thus it is evident, that we muſt needs go elſwher to ſeek out their <hi>generation,</hi> then from Gods <hi>Word</hi> or yet ſound <hi>Antiquity.</hi> In a word they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>foetus neceſſitatis,</hi> the birth and brood of <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> for we find no uſe for them to day, except in ſuch a caſe, where a <hi>buſſines</hi> or <hi>work</hi> in hand, cannot be effectuated and brought to paſſe, but by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175721:14"/>the ſubſidiary help of their ſuffrage, <hi>Majori parte vincente ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorem,</hi> which elſe in reaſon or by force of <hi>Argument</hi> would fall ſhort. May it not juſtly ſeeme according to <hi>Gamaliel</hi> his deciſion in a congener caſe, <hi>That this Counſell or this work hath not been of God, but of men,</hi> Act. 5.38.39. ſeing it is ſo ſoon come to nought, for there is no uſe of them now, their <hi>worke</hi> being accompliſhed which they intended, or in caſe of any new emergent <hi>buſſines,</hi> calling for their ſubſidiary help to hold up that ruinous and decaying <hi>Fabrick</hi> and <hi>structure,</hi> ſo that for the beſt they are but <hi>Nocturni Fungi ex nocturna pluvia nati,</hi> or an untimous <hi>birth</hi> and <hi>abortion,</hi> no ſooner brought to light, then expired.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>THE SECOND Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AERE.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Second Quaere</hi> is, If our <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> did right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie determine anent the receiving in of <hi>Nuncupative Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants</hi> into the boſome of their <hi>Army,</hi> to fight <hi>pro Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria, pro aris et focis,</hi> for <hi>KING, Countrey, Religion, Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Fortunes</hi> in ſuch a nick of time and exigence of affairs, againſt <hi>Forraigne invaſion</hi> of ſo dangerous an <hi>Enemy</hi> infeſting the whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and ſeeking to overturne and raze all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very <hi>foundation;</hi> or pronounced therein <hi>Clave errante. Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merò,</hi> If that ſtood an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull Engagement</hi> with the <hi>Godly Party,</hi> or men of godly <hi>understanding?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT marvels mee not a little, how the <hi>Question</hi> can be thus ſtated and modelled, whereas <hi>adhuc ſub Judice lis est,</hi> which of theſe two conteſting Parties, <hi>Herodians</hi> or <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſo to ſpeak, ſhould be thus branded with the Note of <hi>Malignancy.</hi> I beleeve, That <hi>Veritas</hi> which is <hi>Filia temporis,</hi> TRUETH which ſtands the daughter of time, hath given us ſome farther <hi>light</hi> and clearer <hi>inſight</hi> in this <hi>buſſineſſe;</hi> For how have they I pray you acquitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves here, who were ſo much cryed up for ſole men of known <hi>integrity?</hi> Have they not detected to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175721:14"/>world their deepe masked <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> and ſo bred more nor juſt matter of jealouſie in the hearts of all theſe who are of truly godly <hi>underſtanding? Coelum et terram hîc in teſtes advoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſſem.</hi> 2. Is it not ſtrange, That our new ſtart up <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators</hi> ſhould ſo maligne men under this name and notion of <hi>Malignancy,</hi> whereas they roundly profeſſe their <hi>ignorance</hi> here, of the true <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>marks</hi> from whence they may be diſcerned and dignoſced, as the <hi>Deſire</hi> or <hi>Petition</hi> put up by them, The ſole <hi>Nuncupative Godly Party,</hi> or men of <hi>Godly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> to that Venerable <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> anno 52. for their information hereanent in their 3. <hi>Propoſition</hi> bears, &amp; inſtructs to the full; Now is it not more nor ſtrange, That they ſhould have ſo maligned men under this name and notion, whereas it is not yet conveened upon and condeſcended, what ſtand theſe <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>marks? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi nulla lex, ibi nulla tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſio,</hi> where there is no <hi>Law,</hi> there can be no <hi>Tranſgreſſion.</hi> May it not juſtly ſeeme That <hi>Malignancy</hi> receives <hi>ſubinde,</hi> new <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> or <hi>Marks</hi> according to the various revolution of <hi>Caſes,</hi> and exigence of <hi>times,</hi> or rather men their brain-ſick apprehended <hi>fancies? Nonne haec Eccleſia in Maligno poſita est? Et quae non anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> justè odit coetum hujuſmodi Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium?</hi> 3. I would gladly underſtand the <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pance</hi> here, (where I promiſe to yeeld my ſelf docil and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) Why the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> at firſt, Theſe who found not themſelves fully ſatisfied with the publick <hi>Reſolutions</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> whiles this <hi>work</hi> was but in it <hi>Infancy,</hi> as it were, and ſo when, as I beleeve, it ſtood more <hi>veniall</hi> and <hi>pardonable</hi> to have ſcrupled theranent, were branded with this Note of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy</hi> and <hi>Reproach;</hi> yea, and moſt cruelly perſecuted, as it wer, with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>ſword;</hi> And the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> now, ſo avowedly proteſting againſt all their publick <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> and oppoſing themſelves with an high hand, when this <hi>work</hi> is come to a perfection, to the ſtature of a <hi>Perfect man,</hi> ſhall not onely go unbranded, but go under the name of the <hi>Godly Party,</hi> or men of godly <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and ſhall go over theſe dangerous <hi>rocks,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>Jacture</hi> or <hi>Naufrage,</hi> yea, <hi>turgidis velis, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175721:15"/>ſecnudo,</hi> nay, and ſhould be ſealed in their fore-heads with a <hi>Noli me tangere.</hi> What! Is your ſo glorious a <hi>Sun</hi> come to ſo ſudden a declining? <hi>How is the faithfull City become a harlote, how is your ſilver become droſſe, and your wine mixed with water? how is the ſtrong ſtaffe broken, and the beautifull Rod?</hi> I dare be bold to averre, That the <hi>Approbation</hi> at firſt of the publick <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions</hi> of Church ſtood to many <hi>Cyphers</hi> both in <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> who in effect ſtood more expletive then ſignificative, Their beſt <hi>qualification</hi> and <hi>endowment,</hi> yea ſtood the ſole means of their advancement to the higheſt <hi>roomes</hi> in both. A blind <hi>Obedience</hi> out of an <hi>implicite faith</hi> ſtood for all <hi>qualifications</hi> elſe, and an approven and evidenced <hi>activity</hi> to promove the great &amp; glorious <hi>worke</hi> in hand; This was <hi>Panchreſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, panacaea,</hi> a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>ſalve</hi> againſt all ſores; <hi>Omnibus malis averrumcandis pollens Alexipharmacum;</hi> yea, <hi>veſtis talaris</hi> a faire and goodly <hi>rob</hi> to cover all <hi>nakednes, blemiſhes</hi> or <hi>defects</hi> whatſomever. <hi>It was the balme of Gilead,</hi> and <hi>The tree of the twelve manner of fruits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The grave, learned and judicious <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> have ſufficiently and fully vindicated and aſſerted this <hi>Tenet,</hi> and confirmed the lawfulneſſe thereof in the <hi>Caſe</hi> ſet downe, from the univerſall uncontroverted <hi>practiſe</hi> of all Chriſtian Kingdomes, and <hi>approbation</hi> hereof by the unanimous conſent and judgement of all the ſoundeſt proteſtant <hi>Divines,</hi> in the Caſe of juſt and neceſſarie <hi>defence</hi> againſt forraign <hi>invaſion;</hi> From the very <hi>law</hi> of Nature, which no poſitive <hi>law</hi> of man can infirme or infringe, calling us hereunto, binding and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liedging every <hi>Member</hi> of the politick bodie of a Kingdome, to endeavour to the uttermoſt, the good and preſervation of the whole, and allowing the <hi>Body,</hi> yea, laying an obligation upon ſuch as are in <hi>Eminency</hi> or in <hi>Power,</hi> to call for this help and aſſiſtance at the hands of every <hi>Member;</hi> yea, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no ſmall guilt upon ſuch as ſhall prove deficient, and ſhall withdraw their <hi>ayd</hi> and <hi>asſiſtance</hi> in ſuch an exigence, as <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers</hi> of their Truſt. AND laſt from Gods <hi>Word,</hi> holding out unto us innumberable cleare and ſufficient warrants for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of this <hi>Practiſe.</hi> For re-collection; Is this <hi>practiſe</hi> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175721:15"/>from and by the very <hi>law</hi> of Nature, who can prove ſo farre denatured here, as to maligne the ſame? Stands it juſtifiable by Gods <hi>Word?</hi> Then what man can prove ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and dare make ſo bold, as to ſeclude and diſclude whom God admits? I beleeve, That where God hath not a <hi>mouth</hi> to ſpeak, man ſhould not have an <hi>eare</hi> to heare. <hi>Optimus ſobrietatis terminus eſt Deo loquendi finem faciente, ſapere velle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinere,</hi> It is not ſafe, to co-argue Gods Wiſdom of folly. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vero ſemper conſonat, vos vobis conſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe I finde as yet not a few peſtred and infected with this <hi>leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> I finde me neceſſitated to ſpeak a little more fully of this <hi>Matter,</hi> and to contribute my poore <hi>mite,</hi> out of a willing and free minde for the uſe of this <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle:</hi> for why may it not juſtly ſeem lawfull to theſe, <hi>vel Tauru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> è<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> farina fingere, qui praetenui peculio vitulum vivum divis eluſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nequeunt?</hi> Is it not notourly known, That ſome works of <hi>Necesſity,</hi> which not unfitly is indigitated, <hi>Lex temporis,</hi> The <hi>Law of time,</hi> become juſtifiable, which <hi>extra hunc caſum,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this <hi>caſe</hi> would ceaſe to be ſuch, as the <hi>Diſciples their pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king eares of corne on the Sabbath day. Davids eating of Shew bread, which was onely lawfull for the Prieſts.</hi> Now who dare prove ſo impudent, as to deny an urgent and preſſing <hi>necesſity</hi> here, ſo that it can not be in reaſon challenged of any <hi>unlawfulneſse?</hi> Is it rather wiſely or ſafely done by us, out of uncertaine praeconceived dangers, yea, and but fears of ſuch, and theſe evitable too, from <hi>fellow-ſubjects,</hi> to caſt our ſelves into ſeene and certaine dangers of a forraign <hi>Enemy?</hi> Let me poſe you here, If a <hi>King</hi> can be in reaſon denied the common benefite of the law of the <hi>Subject?</hi> Now ſhall <hi>ſubjects</hi> without chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge make uſe promiſcuouſly of <hi>fellow-ſubjects,</hi> yea, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Native KING, and ſhall we condemne this fact in His Sacred Perſon; to make promiſcuous vſe of His <hi>ſubjects</hi> both in His own juſt and neceſſarie <hi>defence</hi> and theirs too? O for an impartiall <hi>Judge</hi> to decide this controverſie aright! are we not bound and tyed both by <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>KINGS</hi> juſt <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> the <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175721:16"/>ſhall we comply with <hi>Enemies</hi> to both, to the ſubverſion of both? Shall we make ſo great <hi>Conſcience</hi> foreſooth of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heads and articles of our ſworne unto <hi>Covenant,</hi> and none of this maine one? If theſe fiery <hi>Zelots</hi> had lived in Chriſts and his Apoſtles their dayes, doubtleſſe they would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed and maligned the acceſſion of ſo many thouſand ſoules to the Church in one day; who maligned ſo the receiving in of bare <hi>Nuncupative Malignants</hi> into the boſome of their <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Certes,</hi> Theſe differ much in practiſe from that of Chriſts, in receiving in of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>ſinners</hi> May not theſe <hi>Hote-spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited</hi> ſeeme moſt juſtly to be altogether ignorant of the nature &amp; properties of <hi>love</hi> ſet downe <hi>I. Cor.</hi> 13.4.5.6.7.8. <hi>verſes?</hi> Shall Chriſt weeping over <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> profeſſe his great <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> and <hi>earnestneſſe,</hi> to <hi>gather her Children,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their great waywardnes, untowardnes &amp; frowardnes, <hi>as an Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings,</hi> Matth. 23.37. and ſhall we be more propenſe and bently ſet for <hi>diſperſion</hi> and <hi>ſcattering,</hi> then <hi>gathering?</hi> Shall Chriſt profeſſe this to be the <hi>End</hi> of His coming into the World, <hi>to ſeek the loſt ſheepe, to bring againe what had gone astray:</hi> and ſhall theſe who would ſingularly acclaime this <hi>Prerogative</hi> to themſelves, as that they ſtand ſolly his <hi>Miniſters</hi> amidſt a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>defection,</hi> vouchſafe no pains here? It fears me, <hi>The Scribs &amp; Phariſees compaſsing ſea &amp; dry land, to gaine in a Proſelyte,</hi> ſhall riſe up in <hi>judgement</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſtricteſt, rigide and violent <hi>Reformers,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their careleſſe and ſinfull neglect here, and fiery and violent procedure. God is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A God of long <hi>Noſtrills,</hi> and ſo is ſlow to <hi>anger, gentle</hi> and eaſie to be appeaſed; but theſe quite contrarie to Gods Naturall, partake onely in the evill both of the <hi>Cholerian</hi> and the <hi>Melancholian,</hi> they are ſhort ſpirited, ſoone ſet on fire &amp; edge, but their <hi>wrath</hi> is not eaſily quenched and abated, they prove implacable <hi>Edomits</hi> againſt their brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> yea, <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, veniam omnem denegant lapſis;</hi> for I heard this <hi>expreſsion</hi> from ſome of their mouths, That they could ſooner and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier comply with a <hi>Turk,</hi> then with a <hi>Malignant,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175721:16"/>
               <hi>hîc</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no leſſe irreconcilable <hi>enmity,</hi> then twixt the ſeed of the <hi>Woman,</hi> and the ſeed of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> but I ſpare you, <hi>studens Correctioni, parcens pudori.</hi> I could wiſh theſe holy <hi>Zelots</hi> to ſhew me warrants from <hi>Scripture,</hi> the ſafeſt <hi>Rule</hi> and ſureſt <hi>Directory,</hi> Where a <hi>KING, Iudge</hi> or <hi>Ruler</hi> is reproved for making promiſcuous uſe of his <hi>ſubjects,</hi> for the defence of the People of God, and making warre u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their <hi>Enemies;</hi> Nay, and on the contrary, wee ſee them ſadly reproved for their neglect and omisſion here; Hitherto <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants therof, becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> Did not <hi>Gideon</hi> a Iudge of Gods own deſignation, chooſing and ſending out in his might, <hi>Make an Ephod, and put in Ophrah his City, after which all Iſrael went a-whoring: and which thing became a ſnare unto him, and to his houſe, and tended to their deſtruction,</hi> Iudg. 8.27. Now did the people from hence, with our fiery <hi>Zelots,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to go under his <hi>conduct,</hi> or yet receive from his hands or by his means many notable <hi>deliverances?</hi> Nay, was not the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> in ſafety and quietneſſe fourty years in his dayes? Let me poſe theſe ſo <hi>tender-conſcienced</hi> men, if in the 20 of <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.6.7.8. verſes; where, the <hi>Martiall Law</hi> is ſet downe, they do finde this exception of <hi>Malignancy,</hi> ſo much as in the parallel of it? <hi>Certes,</hi> Too vehement a <hi>Purgation</hi> of the Body proves for common well dangerous: for thus the <hi>Vitall ſpirits</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come exhauſted and quite ſpent. I pray you, will yee finde a <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Army</hi> onely <hi>Electorum?</hi> This were to ſeek <hi>Patriam in via,</hi> and to confound <hi>viatores</hi> and <hi>compraehenſores</hi> voyagers and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſors. In the field of the <hi>Militant-Church</hi> upon earth, we will not faill to finde ſtill <hi>tares, cockle</hi> and <hi>darnell</hi> amidſt the beſt <hi>Corne</hi> or <hi>Wheat,</hi> till the day of the great <hi>ſeparation.</hi> When the Lords People went fourth to <hi>Battell,</hi> were they not promiſcuouſly without any inſtituted <hi>Purgation</hi> (a new and unheard of, in Gods Word, piece of policie brought on our ſtage) <hi>gathered as one man from</hi> Dan <hi>to</hi> Beerſheba, <hi>with the land of</hi> Gilead, <hi>unto the Lord in</hi> Mizpeh, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20.1. Nay, and is not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175721:17"/>this called, <hi>A Calling of all generally</hi> without our new modelled <hi>Limitations,</hi> II. Sam. 17.11. Was not the numbering of the People for <hi>Warre,</hi> inſtituted and taken from their ability to carry <hi>Armes</hi> and skill in handling them, and not from any new found out <hi>qualifications?</hi> Reade we not <hi>Sauls</hi> practiſe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah.</hi> without difference, to go forth with him, in the caſe of <hi>Jabeſh-gilead</hi> commended of God, and ſeconded with a <hi>bleſsing,</hi> I. Sam. 11.? In the time of the <hi>Judges,</hi> when the people fell away from the Lord, to or by <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> did not theſe very <hi>Idolaeters</hi> fight the Lords <hi>Battels</hi> and carry the <hi>victory?</hi> Nay, and the very <hi>Judges</hi> themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, who fought the Lords <hi>battels</hi> ſtood not free, under whoſe conduct the people of God obtained many notable <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,</hi> as was preſently inſtanced in the perſon of <hi>Gideon.</hi> Who was more bloudy and wicked then <hi>Joab,</hi> and yet fought the Lords <hi>battels?</hi> Nay, and did not <hi>David</hi> overſee him in a ſeeming prudentiall way for his time, though he gave a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall command to his ſon <hi>Solomon</hi> againſt him, I. <hi>Kings,</hi> 2. ? Did not <hi>Abner</hi> make a bloudy <hi>warre</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> and yet he did not ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence to make uſe of him? Wer not theſe men, who were with <hi>David</hi> when he fled from SAUL, <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws</hi> &amp; <hi>Male-contents,</hi> Now forbore he to make his beſt vſe of theſe <hi>Malignants,</hi> to ſpeak in the language of <hi>Babel?</hi> Nay, Did he not welcome <hi>Simei,</hi> who had formerly curſed him, &amp; ſtood his moſt cruell <hi>Enemy</hi> in the time of his <hi>adverſity:</hi> and that notwithſtanding of <hi>Abiſha's</hi> inſtancie to the contrary? I wiſh wee ſhould propoſe before our eyes <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe and example (who was called a man according to Gods owne heart) for our ſafer direction, and better regulation of our <hi>Comportment</hi> here. <hi>Spectemus hanc Cynoſuram;</hi> Now <hi>David</hi> ſent to <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the prieſts, to rebuke the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Eleders of <hi>Judah,</hi> to bring againe the <hi>King</hi> to his houſe, whereas the people conteſted and ſtrove here in forewardnes, and that from an <hi>argument</hi> taken from his intereſt in them, &amp; their attingency to him, ſciz. That they were his <hi>Brethren,</hi> his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175721:17"/>
               <hi>fleſh</hi> &amp; his <hi>bones;</hi> Nay, and he ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> who had been a <hi>Ring-leader</hi> in a preſent rebellion with <hi>Abſalom</hi> againſt him, willing them to make uſe of this ſame argument with him; Nay, and promiſing fairely to make him Captaine in <hi>Ioabs</hi> ſtead, which he accordingly performed, did not God ſecond this with a ſuccesfull blesſing? <hi>Did he not bow all the hearts of the men of Iudah as of one man,</hi> II. Sam. 19.11.12.13.14. verſ. To apply here home, Why might not, or may not our KING uſe the ſame <hi>policie</hi> even to reclaime, and win in the hearts of theſe, who had been <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> in a known and open <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> againſt him, farre more to make uſe of His loyall <hi>ſubjects?</hi> May I not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence thus ſafely argue &amp; reaſon? Do not all in whom he hath a-like common <hi>interest</hi> ſtand juſtly liable in, &amp; to the ſame common <hi>duty?</hi> What wiſdome or prudence were it in a common <hi>Combuſtion</hi> and <hi>Conflagration,</hi> to debarre &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any from contributing their ayd &amp; asſiſtance, for quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and extinguiſhing the ſame? Let me poſe them here, if theſe whom they ſo odiouſly traduce under the name of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,</hi> had or have no part or right in their KING, that they might be ſo farre neglected, as that neither their <hi>advice</hi> nor <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> ſhould be ſought or called for, for his <hi>ſafety</hi> and <hi>preſervation,</hi> 2. Sam. 19.43? I would gladly underſtand the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of difference here, why theſe whom they are pleaſed to traduce under ſuch odious nomenclatures as <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>Engagers,</hi> whereas <hi>adhuc ſub judice lis ſit,</hi> whether the <hi>Engagers</hi> for their <hi>KING,</hi> or theſe for the Common <hi>Enemy,</hi> may, yea and juſtly ſhould be holden and accounted true and reall <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants?</hi> Why I ſay theſe were admitted, <hi>ad omnia interiora ſacra, ad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the participation of the ſacred <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and yet denied admiſſion into the boſom of an <hi>Army,</hi> alleadged raiſed for the good of the wholl king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in common, wherein they have their juſt intereſt? Is there greater <hi>Religion</hi> to be ſhewed here in <hi>This,</hi> then in that <hi>Other?</hi> May it not juſtly fear me, That as <hi>Ieroboa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> made religion ſubſervient to his <hi>by-ends,</hi> whereas hee made the two golden <hi>Calves,</hi> and ſet the one in <hi>Dan,</hi> and the other in <hi>Bethel,</hi> yea, &amp;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175721:18"/>made a <hi>Temple;</hi> where <hi>Altars</hi> were built for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or <hi>an houſe of high places, and made Prieſts of the loweſt of the People</hi> (with our pious and zealous <hi>Reformers</hi> to day) <hi>Which were not of the ſons of Levi,</hi> pretending one thing, The <hi>Eaſe of the people:</hi> but intending another, <hi>To keepe the hearts of the People, that they ſhould not turne back againe unto their Lord, even to Rehaboam King of Judah,</hi> I. King. 12. That it did ſo go and fare with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, that they made <hi>Relegion</hi> but tributary and ſubſervient to their own <hi>by-ends:</hi> for may it not now clearely be ſeen; That their <hi>Pretenſes</hi> or <hi>pretexts,</hi> and their <hi>Reall intentions</hi> have never reciprocated and retro-commeated? That returned Anſwere of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> to <hi>David, bidding him go downe to his houſe,</hi> II. Sam. 11. <hi>Whereas the Ark, and Iſrael and Iudah were ſojourning in tents: and his Lord Ioab, and the ſervants of his Lord were encamped in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fields, that it was not time to him to go down to his houſe,</hi> may prove much uſefull and ſubſervient to the <hi>Purpoſe</hi> in hand: for was it time, I pray you, for any <hi>Subjects</hi> promiſcuouſly, when <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>Kingdome, PRINCE</hi> and <hi>Subject,</hi> all ſtood in danger, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>Enemy</hi> infeſting the Land, to ſit the <hi>Charge,</hi> not anſwere the <hi>Call,</hi> or for any to withdraw or with-hold their <hi>aide</hi> and <hi>aſsiſtance</hi> in ſo preſſing an <hi>exigence,</hi> or yet for the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> to open their mouths ſo wide againſt a preſent, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie &amp; juſt <hi>expedition?</hi> I could be eaſily &amp; no leſſe juſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced &amp; induced to believe here, That <hi>ſalus populi,</hi> ſhould have ſtood <hi>ſuprema lex.</hi> But <hi>Quod dolendum, juxta ac pudendum,</hi> our violent <hi>Reformers</hi> have overturned all; They have brought on our ſtage all new <hi>Rules</hi> for ordering of things, <hi>Novam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulam Credendi, novam faciendi, novam precaudi,</hi> whereas the Lord forbids us, <hi>To take His Name in vaine.</hi> How many have they adacted to conceive many blinde <hi>Oaths,</hi> which is a flate <hi>Taking of His Name in vaine?</hi> Nay and how many have they enforced to ſwear againſt the very light of their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not onely doubtingly, yea and to conceive a quite <hi>Contrary-Oath</hi> to that whereunto they had ſworne formerly? Now I beleeve, That two <hi>Contrary-Oaths</hi> cannot be averred to have their due qualifications, to be in <hi>Trueth,</hi> in <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> and in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175721:18"/>
               <hi>Judgement;</hi> Have they not profeſſed <hi>Perjury</hi> in the perſon of their Characterized ones, to ſtand but a <hi>Perſonall infirmitie,</hi> for extenuation of that haynous ſin in men of their ſtampe? Have they not pleaded for <hi>Muther</hi> &amp; for the <hi>Murtherers</hi> vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; abſolution, in the perſon of ſome rightly affected to their <hi>Worke</hi> in hand? Have they not taught <hi>diſobedience</hi> to <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Powers,</hi> yea, and ſeverly puniſhed others for teaching <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> as their <hi>Doctrine</hi> by them formerly condemned of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe,</hi> upon after recognition declared <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>orthodox,</hi> can make faith? How many have they enforced to <hi>beare falſe witneſſe</hi> againſt themſelves, by the acknowledging parforce of the equity of their moſt unjuſt <hi>ſentences,</hi> which is no leſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then to beare the ſame againſt their Neighbour? How have they not onely overſeene, but beſides a <hi>Toleration,</hi> patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized <hi>uncleanneſſe</hi> in the perſon of their ſealed ones? <hi>Numerò,</hi> throughout all, contrarie to <hi>Tertullians</hi> preſcript, That <hi>Fides non aeſtimanda ex perſonis, ſed perſonae ex fide,</hi> They paſſed their conſtructions upon men their <hi>actings</hi> of whatſomever kinde, as they did favour or disfavour the Actours. <hi>Non Abel è donis, ob Abelem donae placebant;</hi> As to the RULE of <hi>Faith,</hi> Their <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> is made the ſole Authentike RULE. As to the RULE of <hi>Prayer,</hi> they not onely caſhiered that patern of <hi>Prayer</hi> preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Chriſt, but blaſphemouſly traduced it under the name of a <hi>Nocent Ceremony,</hi> and conſtructed of the bare conceiving of it, at any publick ſervice, a Note of Malignancy, <hi>Quae hos dementia caepit.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="objections">
               <head>EXCEPTIONS <hi>or</hi> OBIECTIONS.</head>
               <p>I meete here with three maine <hi>Exceptions</hi> taken againſt this <hi>Trueth,</hi> though ſo clearely evidenced and fully vindicated and aſſerted, or <hi>Objections</hi> builded upon weak and infirme <hi>Topicks,</hi> whereby they go about to infirme and weaken this <hi>Trueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Firſt is, from that <hi>Fact</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from his Army, <hi>The houndreth thouſand valiant men of Iſrael, who came to him out of Ephraim,</hi> II. Chron. 25.</item>
                  <item>The Second is, from <hi>Gideons</hi> purging of his Army <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.</item>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175721:19"/>
                  <item>The Third is, That thus All former <hi>Principles</hi> ſo fairlie and firmely laid, are hereby quite <hi>inverted, changed</hi> and <hi>overturned.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>To overrune theſe <hi>Calaemo currente,</hi> By a running pen.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. To the Firſt. <hi>Nihil hîc Praeſidii,</hi> There is no help from this <hi>Mountaine:</hi> for did not <hi>Amaziah</hi> make a promiſcuous <hi>Choyce</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> of all thoſe, that were able to beare <hi>Armes,</hi> handle <hi>speare</hi> and <hi>ſhield,</hi> to go forth to warre, without making any difference? Now who dare prove ſo impudent as to averr, That in ſuch a numerous <hi>Army,</hi> there was no mixture of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi> or to ſpeake by accommodation, of <hi>Covenanter</hi> and <hi>Anti-Covenanter,</hi> as wee learne now to ſpeak?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Amaziah</hi> ſtood here inſtructed with an expreſſe <hi>Warrant</hi> from the Man of GOD, for his inſtituted <hi>Purgation</hi> and <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> ſtraitly inhibiting and diſcharging him, <hi>to let the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Iſrael go with him, becauſe the Lord was not with them, II.</hi> Chron. 25.7. Now inſtruct the like <hi>Warrant</hi> for this your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <hi>Purgation,</hi> and ſo yee ſhall juſtifie and warrant your <hi>Practiſe.</hi> I beleeve, That this ſort of <hi>oeconomy</hi> is now ceaſed, God doeth not ſo ſpeake to us now in theſe laſt dayes. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The hundreth thouſand men of Iſrael, who were ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were men hired out of the ten <hi>Tribes,</hi> who had made a former <hi>revolt</hi> both from GOD and their King: But theſe men whom they would have purged out of their <hi>Army,</hi> were men fearing God and their King, or as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Fearing God and honouring their King,</hi> and ſo <hi>hîc magnum</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>labes, lacuna, disſidium,</hi> There is a great <hi>diſtance</hi> here. IT were to be wiſhed, that ſome <hi>Armies</hi> with them had not almoſt altogether conſiſted of open or masked <hi>Rebells.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. IT is not ſafe argumenting from an <hi>Idolatrous King,</hi> to a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> for this <hi>Amaziah</hi> (whereas he ſhould have given <hi>Praiſe</hi> to God for his <hi>victory</hi>) he fell foullie away to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> for <hi>hee brought the gods of the Children of Seir, and ſet them up to be his gods, and worſhiped them, and burned incenſe to them,</hi> ibid. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. Nay, and a great many of his own <hi>ſubjects,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had promiſcuouſly admitted, <hi>ſacrificed &amp; burned incenſe in the high places,</hi> II. King. 14.4.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:175721:19"/>
                  <p n="5">5. From a <hi>Contre-mand,</hi> to aſſociat with <hi>Idolaters</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners,</hi> to a <hi>Poſitive Commaend,</hi> to ſeclude and exclude <hi>Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubjects</hi> and <hi>Profeſſours.</hi> The <hi>Conſequence</hi> ſtands <hi>inconſequent,</hi> Thus this ſtrong <hi>Hold</hi> being diſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tled, <hi>Ad quod ſe recipient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verticulum,</hi> To what ſtarting <hi>hole</hi> can they betake them now?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To the Second. <hi>GIDEONS Purgation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Certes,</hi> Me thinks, This is no leſſe impertinently allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the juſtification of a called for <hi>Purgation</hi> of our <hi>Army:</hi> for he had an immediat and expreſſe <hi>Warrant</hi> from God, to qualifie and juſtifie that his <hi>Purgation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. This his <hi>Purgation</hi> was inſtituted and made upon a farre different reſpect, <hi>Leſt Iſrael ſhould have vaunted themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord, and ſaid, That their own hand had ſaved them,</hi> as the TEXT bears.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. GOD commanded this <hi>Purgation</hi> for a ſpeciall <hi>End,</hi> to prove Himſelf <hi>To be the Lord of Hoſts, Who ſaveth not by ſword or bow, speare or ſhield: but can ſave by few, as by many;</hi> Now <hi>Deus non ſibi, ſed nobis ponit, fert legem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Lord gave <hi>GIDEON</hi> a <hi>ſigne,</hi> wherby he might know and diſcerne theſe whom the Lord would have to go with him, ſciz. <hi>The lapping of the water,</hi> And this for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Lord aſſured them by a <hi>Dreame,</hi> and the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, of the <hi>Victory</hi> by a few: Now I believe, That the Lord dealt not ſo with the Army of our <hi>Water-lappers; Omnia haec hîc deſiderabantur,</hi> all theſe were here wanting: and ſo the <hi>Event</hi> comproved <hi>That God was not with them,</hi> and that their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted purgation of <hi>Armies,</hi> ſtood unwarrantable and unju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To the Third. The <hi>Change &amp; Alteration of Principles.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Here the Weſt-land and North-land <hi>Donatists</hi> in common make bold to arceſſe our Repreſentive Church of <hi>Defection</hi> and <hi>Apoſtaſie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. I would learne of theſe Seraphick &amp; enlightned <hi>Doctours,</hi> What ſort of <hi>Principle</hi> this can be called and accounted, To deny <hi>Fellow-ſubjects</hi> this liberty in common, to fight <hi>pro Patria.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175721:20"/>pro aris et focis,</hi> for <hi>KING, Countrey, Religion, Lives, Liberties, Fortunes</hi> in ſuch an <hi>Exigency</hi> of ſo neeſſarie and preſſing a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> againſt a <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> infeſting the whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and ſeeking the <hi>overthrow,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſubverſion</hi> or <hi>ſupplantation</hi> of all? If this be a <hi>Principle</hi> of divine irrefragable and immutable <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> or of humane <hi>Policy, Inſtitution</hi> &amp; <hi>Invention,</hi> ſet onely on foot by man, for his own ſiniſter and <hi>By-ends,</hi> as a meane moſt powerfull to keep the <hi>ſword</hi> and all <hi>Power</hi> elſe in their owne hands, as they ſcrupled not openly to profeſſe their <hi>feare</hi> here of the ſame danger from others; In a word, Leſt they ſhould be cryed downe, &amp; others up to ſpeak hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>Certes,</hi> This was a deep <hi>Policy</hi> from the very forge of <hi>hell,</hi> to diveſt the KING of His juſt <hi>Power,</hi> which they call the chief place of <hi>Truſt,</hi> to ſtirre up the one part of His <hi>ſubjects,</hi> and that not a little conſiderable, to a juſt <hi>jealouſie,</hi> if not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and ſo denude Him of their juſt and due <hi>ayde</hi> &amp; <hi>aſſiſtance:</hi> and ſo to expoſe Him to the <hi>mercy,</hi> rather <hi>Crueltie</hi> of a moſt dangerous <hi>Enemy</hi> infeſting Him &amp; the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in common. <hi>Numerò,</hi> to redact His <hi>Monarchie,</hi> into an <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> or <hi>Oligarchy,</hi> nay, into a <hi>Democracy</hi> and popular <hi>Confuſion:</hi> for <hi>Virtus quò unitior, eò fortior;</hi> and <hi>ubi fingli pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſinguli vincuntur; Factions</hi> make <hi>fractions,</hi> and theſe are the certaine forrunners of an unavoidable after <hi>Confuſion.</hi> I beleeve, That I have found out <hi>Labans</hi> gods for all <hi>Rachel</hi> her <hi>Cunning,</hi> and cloſe ſitting on them, and labouring to hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from our fight.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Yee do well to call this a <hi>Principle:</hi> for <hi>Principia praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda, non probanda,</hi> as they ſpeak in Schooles: Thus it is ſafeſt to preſume this for a <hi>Principle:</hi> for ſure I am, That ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prove able, to prove and inſtruct it by any, demenſtiative <hi>Proofe, Note</hi> or <hi>Mark,</hi> as is cleare and evident out of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes;</hi> And ſo the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> which they kithe and bewray here, is onely <hi>depraedatrix,</hi> a <hi>spoyling or robbing Philoſophy,</hi> for through the deceit therof, with the little, but pernicious <hi>skill</hi> they have, they have done what in them lay, to have carryed away a faire <hi>ſpoyle</hi> and goodlie <hi>booty, By their vaine traditions
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175721:20"/>and elements of the World, and not of Chriſt,</hi> Coll. 2.8. Nay, and overturned both <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and brought all under <hi>deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If wee ſhall be pleaſed to conſtrue of things and meaſure them <hi>ab eventu,</hi> What better ſucceſſe had that <hi>Weſtland Army,</hi> which conſiſted to their judgement of meere <hi>Water-lappers?</hi> Was God found to have been with that <hi>Army?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. What neede you to ſtand upon this, to change and alter ſuch a <hi>Principle,</hi> ſince you dared to make bold to invert <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of a farre higher nature? For of old <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> ſtood not obligatory <hi>in foro externo,</hi> till the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ſhould have interponed <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or his <hi>Sanction,</hi> and ſo theſe were confirmed in Parliaments: but now the <hi>Chaſe</hi> is turned, the <hi>caſe</hi> quite altered; By your <hi>Eccleſiasticall Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> you made bold to confirme or infirme <hi>Parliaments, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Engagements,</hi> and what not? Did yee not thus tranſcend your ſphaere, and out-repaſſe your Line, <hi>Non ſic fuit ab initio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Did not your Weſtland <hi>Donatists</hi> proteſting againſt their KING His bare ſitting with them in <hi>Councell,</hi> let be preſiding. Whoſe proper <hi>right</hi> it is <hi>praeeſſe externo Regimini,</hi> to moderate the externall government of the <hi>Church,</hi> invert a <hi>Principle</hi> of a higher nature? <hi>Diſtant hac duo, Potestas Eccleſiastica propriè ſic dicta, et poteſtas circa res eccleſiaſticas verſans;</hi> The Civil <hi>Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat</hi> ſtands <hi>Epiſcopus ad extra,</hi> as CONSTANTINE the great termed Himſelf, as the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> ſtand <hi>Epiſcopi ad intra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Let me poſe you, If <hi>ſimilarie parts</hi> be not of the ſame <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure</hi> and <hi>nature,</hi> and ſo what <hi>caſe</hi> hath behapned or befallen the <hi>Church,</hi> in changing and altering theſe her firſt <hi>Principles,</hi> might not have befallen her at the firſt ſubſterning them for <hi>Principles?</hi> What I pray you could have priviledged your <hi>Church</hi> from <hi>Errability</hi> or <hi>fallability</hi> at the firſt more then now? I wiſh from mine heart, ſhe had never made farther nor fouler <hi>defection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Is it not agreed upon amongſt all ſound <hi>Divines,</hi> That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>ſentences</hi> or <hi>decrees</hi> of <hi>oecumenicall Councels</hi> ſtood not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatorie, <hi>propter authoritatem pronuntiantis, ſed propter verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175721:21"/>aequitatem</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>pondus ſententiae,</hi> becauſe of the Authority of the <hi>Pronouncer,</hi> but for the <hi>Trueth, Equity</hi> and <hi>Weyght</hi> of the <hi>ſentence?</hi> Hitherto maks that <hi>dispute</hi> twixt <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Maximinus</hi> an <hi>Arrian;</hi> where both roundly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, That the Authority of <hi>Councels</hi> is not binding. Is it not a received <hi>Maxime</hi> amongſt the Iuriſts, <hi>Sententia le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus contraria, ipſo jure eſt nulla?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. I beleeve, That the Change and alteration of all <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> formerly holden, cannot in ſafe conſtruction bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Apoſtaſie;</hi> Turned <hi>Paul</hi> an <hi>Apostate,</hi> whereas of a ſtrict <hi>Phariſee,</hi> he turned an <hi>Apoſtle?</hi> or <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he left off to be a <hi>Manichaean,</hi> or when he had his <hi>Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> Moſes <hi>was learned in all the wiſdome of the Egyptians,</hi> Act. 7.22. now did he alwayes hold faſt all their <hi>Principles?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Doeth not the <hi>Apostle</hi> even command a certaine <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> by an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Let every one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part or apoſtate from <hi>iniquity.</hi> Would to God there wer more of ſuch <hi>Apoctates.</hi> Now ſuch is this, if it may be called <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>Quod tranſcendit omne mirum,</hi> How have theſe rigide &amp; ſo ſtrict Obſervers of <hi>Principles,</hi> ſo deeply forgotten themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, that almoſt they have retro-graded and troden under foot the greateſt part of all their prior <hi>principles? Feare</hi> here ſtands <hi>the Law of time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. I pray you, did you not invert and quite overturne a <hi>Principle</hi> of a far higher <hi>nature</hi> and deeper <hi>Concernment,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in your ſo much cryed up <hi>Covenant,</hi> as of a divine frame, you limited your <hi>obedience</hi> due to your KING, <hi>in the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion,</hi> whereas in the <hi>Confesſion of Faith</hi> homologa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by both the Nations, you ſtick not roundly to confeſſe &amp; acknowledge, that neither <hi>Infidelity</hi> nor <hi>difference</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> maks voide the <hi>Magiſtrats</hi> juſt and legall <hi>Authority,</hi> nor doeth free the people from their due <hi>obedience? Mendax oportet ſit ſui ſemper memor.</hi> O! What an <hi>Acataſtaſie</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> would this bring in Kingdoms, where <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> ſtand of contrarie <hi>profeſſions?</hi> I was taught that every one ſhould live
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175721:21"/>peaceably, under the laws of the Lord of the Territory, wherein he liveth.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Do yee not ſubſterne and lay this as a firme <hi>principle,</hi> &amp; of undoubted divine <hi>Authority,</hi> the abjuration of the <hi>Articles</hi> of PERTH? Now I would poſe you, If Chriſt preſcribed any certaine <hi>geſture</hi> to be obſerved at the perception of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt;</hi> Nay, or if he uſed the <hi>geſture</hi> of ſitting Himſelf, wherein they place ſo great <hi>Religion?</hi> If this particular <hi>geſture</hi> ſtand <hi>instituti</hi> or <hi>praecepti divini,</hi> how ſhould they not condemne the <hi>French-Church</hi> who adminiſter it <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> or en paſſant, and ſo arceſſe her of <hi>Apoſtaſie:</hi> for what is preceptory, is to all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory? I pray you, Is the different eſtimation of dayes, a <hi>principle</hi> of divine, irrefragable and immutable <hi>verity?</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, beſides that both in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Christian-Church</hi> ſome <hi>Dayes</hi> have been had in greater <hi>veneration,</hi> That the <hi>Apostle</hi> willeth every one anent his different eſtimation of them <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. to labour for a <hi>pleroforie</hi> or <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of aſſurance for his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting hereanent, <hi>Let each of theſe, him who eſteemeth one day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another, &amp; him who puts no difference here, but eſteemeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day a-like, do it to the Lord,</hi> and all ſhall go right. <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God ſtands not in meat &amp; drink,</hi> (where <hi>omnia congenerae</hi> are to be underſtood) <hi>but in righteouſneſſe, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> alace whereas they have ſo buſily and painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie gone about to bring in a Reformation, in <hi>Circumstantials</hi> or matters of a midle <hi>nature</hi> or <hi>indifferency,</hi> they have inverted and overturned many <hi>ſubſtantials,</hi> nay, <hi>Luxarunt et laxarunt Compagem utriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Tabulae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. What needed you to ſcruple much here, anent the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and alteration of this <hi>Principle,</hi> Anent the <hi>qualification</hi> of men to be received into the boſome of an <hi>Army,</hi> whereas you made no conſcience to invert &amp; overturne a <hi>Principle</hi> of far higher <hi>Nature</hi> and greater <hi>Concernment,</hi> viz. That having ſworne in <hi>Covenant</hi> to maintaine the KINGS juſt <hi>Greatnes,</hi> (where under this word, <hi>juſt,</hi> experience hath proven many hid pieces of <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty</hi> to have lyen lurking) &amp; <hi>Authority,</hi> you ſurrendred Him into the hands of His <hi>Enemies?</hi> IT cannot but wonder me, you
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175721:22"/>ſhould ſtraine a <hi>Gnate,</hi> having ſwallowed a <hi>Camel;</hi> Was this to make conſcience of that ſacred <hi>oath</hi> tendred by you to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine His Sacred Perſon and juſt Greatneſſe? In an <hi>Oath</hi> we ought no leſſe heedily to look, <hi>Cui,</hi> then <hi>quid juraverimus</hi> as the ſchoolmen teach us, whoſe <hi>Name</hi> is interponed, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Name</hi> of God, <hi>Whom-unto</hi> rather, then <hi>where-unto.</hi> As <hi>David</hi> reported well to <hi>Abner,</hi> I. Sam. 26.15. with no leſſe juſt matter may I here to you. Were not ye onely men of known <hi>integrity,</hi> the <hi>Charactarized Ones,</hi> and none like you in all the kingdome, for <hi>Loyalty, valour,</hi> &amp; <hi>gallantry,</hi> wherfore did not you keep better your LORD, the KING, wheras a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>Enemy</hi> was ſeeking His overthrow &amp; of this whole kingdom? Alace, wheras formerly we were accounted men of unſtained and untainted <hi>Loyalty,</hi> yea and of no ſmall <hi>valour</hi> &amp; <hi>proveſſe,</hi> throughout all Nations, as that we were admitted &amp; received by forraign Kings, to ſtand their <hi>Guardians</hi> or <hi>guard du Corps,</hi> as they ſpeak; Now with <hi>Reuben</hi> we have fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our <hi>dignity,</hi> and loſſed our <hi>excellency,</hi> and moſt juſtly incurred the ſtaine &amp; note of <hi>Infamy</hi> at home (in that we tendred not more the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> &amp; <hi>ſafety</hi> of our KING) to our everlaſting <hi>diffamation</hi> and never dying reproach; <hi>loquetur poſteritas.</hi> whereas you fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretexe for your juſtification, that they keeped not <hi>Covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> here with you or <hi>Capitulation;</hi> This will not cover your <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes,</hi> but your <hi>heels</hi> ſhall be found bare: for <hi>Non faciendum malum, ut eveniat bonum,</hi> we muſt not do evill, that good may come of it; far leſſe, for an uncertaine <hi>after-good,</hi> commit a certain preſent <hi>evill.</hi> Is not our whole <hi>duty</hi> we owe our KING, borne upon us by <hi>Negatives?</hi> Now as the Schoolmen teach us here, <hi>Negative precepts</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands</hi> bind and obliege as <hi>ad ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> ſo <hi>pro ſemper,</hi> as to all times, ſo for all times, Nay, &amp; doth not the <hi>Scripure</hi> bind up the whole man and the whole of man here, <hi>totum hominem, et totum hominis, tongue, hand</hi> &amp; <hi>thought,</hi> ſo that albeit <hi>cogitationis poenam nemo patiatur in foro ſoli, in foro po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli</hi> it goeth not unpuniſhed, ſo that it is not ſafe for us to <hi>curſe the King, no not in our thought</hi> Eccl. 10.20. and it is worthy our beſt and narroweſt remark, who ſhall ſtand the <hi>diſcovers</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealers</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:175721:22"/>hereof, <hi>for a bird of the ayre ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi> May not this ſtrick us with <hi>feare</hi> &amp; <hi>terrour,</hi> to prove deficient in our bonden <hi>duty</hi> to out Sacred and dread SOVERAIGN? As we reply to <hi>Papiſts</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to juſtifie their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> averring that they ſet up I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, <hi>non ad culium, ſed ad uſum historicum;</hi> That it is better and ſafer <hi>lapidem offendiculi è via conſulari tollere, quàm ponere,</hi> with whatſomever <hi>Cautions</hi> or <hi>Caveats</hi> over the head of it: ſo may I here; IT had proven better &amp; ſafer, to have keeped our LORD the KING and capitulated with them, then upon the ſurrendering of Him into their hands, to truſt to their <hi>after-Capitulation.</hi> Do not your <hi>Ministery</hi> diſcover both your &amp; their own <hi>Skirts,</hi> wheras from <hi>Chayre</hi> they make bold to atteſt God, how evill yee ſtand acquitted for your <hi>Loyaltie</hi> and good <hi>ſervice</hi> done them, which hath proven <hi>diſloyaltie</hi> and bad <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> to your Supreame LORD of Heaven, and His Deputy upon earth.</p>
                  <p>IT is a received MAXIME; <hi>Quod quis per alium facit, hoe per ſe meritè facere videtur,</hi> yea, &amp; there is another to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Quod quis non vetat, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt, quod vetare tenetur, is jubet.</hi> Thus I ſee not how you can ſtand free of the crying <hi>bloud-guilt</hi> of your Sacred SOVERAIGN. Do not, I pray you, <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> yea, and <hi>Gregory</hi> too, averre; <hi>Non carere ſcrupulo ſocietatis oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culto, ubi quis manifesto ſceleri deſinit obviare.</hi> I dare be bold to averre, That unſoundnes of <hi>Doctrine</hi> hath done no leſſe harm, then the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Perſecution</hi> throughout the whole buſſines. As is recorded of ARRIUS <hi>Hereſie,</hi> That it did more hurt to the Church of God, then the <hi>ten bloudie Perſecutions.</hi> IT fears me, That it may be truely ſaid of our Church, for all the cryed up <hi>glorie</hi> of this great and glorious work of <hi>Reformation, That her works are not to be found perfect before God,</hi> as is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Revel. 3.2. Nay, <hi>And that Christ hath not a few things againſt her,</hi> as is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Pergamus.</hi> Revel. 2.12.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. I cannot underſtand upon what warrantable ground this can be goodly called a <hi>Principle,</hi> To deny <hi>fellow-ſubjects</hi> liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175721:23"/>to fight <hi>pro patria, pro aris et focis,</hi> for KING, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whereas Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> determines quite to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: for he ſhews that <hi>In the multitude of people ſtands or conſiſts the Kings honour,</hi> as on the other hand, <hi>In this defect or want His deſtruction,</hi> Prov. 14.28. The <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ſmart</hi> whereof, wee have found by ſad and dolefull <hi>experience.</hi> For <hi>Cloſure,</hi> Let me recommend both to <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> throughout this kingdome, <hi>Mordicai</hi> his healthfull advice to queene <hi>Esther; For if thou altogether holdeſt thy peace at this time, then ſhall there Enlargement and deliverance ariſe to the Jews from another place, but thou and thy fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> Eſther 4.14. So <hi>accomodate ad ſubjectum,</hi> by accomodation to the <hi>ſubject</hi> or <hi>purpoſe</hi> in hand; If you ſhall prove deficient and wanting to repreſſe, yea and redreſſe all formerly <hi>Diſorders</hi> both in <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and carefully repaire by gone <hi>ſlipps</hi> &amp; <hi>miſgivings,</hi> theſe ſhall prove but the bare and naked beginnings of greater <hi>After-ſorrows</hi> and <hi>Calamities,</hi> and God ſhall not faile or prove wanting, to foreſee and provide, for the good and well of His own <hi>Zion.</hi> As on the other hand, Queen <hi>Esther</hi> her practiſe in undertaking the <hi>ſute,</hi> by taking her life, as it were, in her ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; <hi>If I periſh, I periſh,</hi> to your imitation; That ſo diſreſpecting, as it were, the quality of whatſoever <hi>oppoſers,</hi> and laying aſide all <hi>Panik-fears,</hi> you would endevour to break thorow all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>Letts</hi> and thwarting <hi>obſtacles:</hi> &amp; make the peace of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> your chiefeſt joy &amp; aime, and that ſo according to Chriſts preſcription, you would at laſt, <hi>Render to Caeſar, the things that be Caeſars, as to God, the things that are Gods.</hi> Nay, &amp; I would wiſh from mine heart, That as you have committed, by following <hi>Achitophelian counſell,</hi> a tranſcendent, exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and unparelleled <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> by ſurrendering up of your KING into the hands of His cruell &amp; bloudie <hi>Enemies,</hi> yea, &amp; whereas Hee came of His own accord under your wings to truſt, whereby you have done what in you lay, to precide and cut off all juſt hopes of all after <hi>Reconciliation.</hi> So now follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example of the <hi>Aramits,</hi> you would in all <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and out of a deep reſentment of <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>ſorrow,</hi> ſtay and preſent
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175721:23"/>your ſelves to His Son, your Sacred and dread now SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGN, with <hi>rops</hi> about your <hi>necks,</hi> relying on His <hi>Mercieful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> &amp; you might yet expect ſome favourable <hi>aſpects</hi> &amp; <hi>reſpects:</hi> for, <hi>NOBILIS EST IRA LEONIS, parcere ſubjectis et de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellare ſuperbos;</hi> And ſure I am, That He will account it His no leſſe glory, to ſucceed His Royall FATHER of Bleſſed and never dying Memory, Who lived a <hi>SAINT,</hi> and dyed a <hi>MARTYRE,</hi> in, and to His moſt rare and commendable Chriſtian <hi>Vertues,</hi> then in, and to His <hi>Crownes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by <hi>James Brown,</hi> APRIL, 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175721:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
